<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="104"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                             TABLE OF CONTENTS                                               3
                                                                                             4
Executive Summary                                                                            6
Introduction
Description of the College                                                                   8
Vision, Mission and Goals of the College                                                     48
                                                                                             66
Narrative Profile                                                                            84
Instruction
Extension
Research
Faculty Development

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

               Executive Summary

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 2]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                   INTRODUCTION

         Each university, campus, college, and institute has its way of telling about
their institution. The instruction, research and extension are being influenced by
the processes and procedures by which the institution makes its decisions under
the context in which teaching and learning takes place. The university’s vision,
mission, goals pave way towards accomplishing its objectives.

         Many factors contribute to the overall narrative such as the curriculum, the
physical facilities, faculty profile, research and extension activities, an
identification of stakeholders and their engagement, the trends and issues
affecting the institution, and the kinds of programs and services that a college
implements to support student learning.

         The purpose of the Executive Summary (ES) is to provide a college with
an opportunity to describe in narrative form the strengths and challenges it
encounters. By doing so, the public, the members of the accrediting agency and
the college itself will have a more complete picture of how its unit perceives itself
and the process of self-reflection for continuous improvement. This summary is
structured for the college to reflect on how it provides teaching and learning on a
day to day basis.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 3]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                      DESCRIPTION OF THE COLLEGE

         The Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (BSCS) at DMMMSU-Agoo
started its formal operation under the Institute of Computer Science in June
1999, pursuant to Board Resolution No. 98-046.

         It was conceived in the College of Sciences under the Deanship of Dr.
Inocencio D. Mangaoang, Jr. in 1997 and was thoroughly prepared by the
Mathematics Department chaired by Dr. Editha T. Vasay.

         The establishment of the BSCS program under the Institute was made
possible due to the steadfast support of then President, Dr. Manuel T. Corpus,
and South La Union Campus Chancellor, Dr. Amelia O. Bacungan.

         On its first year of operation, Dr. Vasay was designated as the Institute
Director and was concurrently the Chairman of the Mathematics Department of
the College of Sciences. The core faculty members were only 6 (six) and
eventually additional faculty members were hired.

         On its first year of operation, 31 students were enrolled. The enrolment
increased and exceeded its expected number of students because of the
demand for an IT course. Students are admitted based on the university
admission test with the prescribed standard of admission for BS Computer
Science.

         During the summer of 2007, the institute administrators, faculty and staff
prepared the documents and facilities in applying for the ladderization of the
BSCS program. The institute also passed the assessment of the Technical
Education and Skills Development Authority (TESDA) and was granted authority
to offer the Programs: PC Operations NC II, Computer Hardware servicing NC II
and Programming NC IV on April 26, 2007.

         The ladderization of the BSCS program was granted a Certificate of
Authority to operate effective SY 2007-2008 by the Commission on Higher
Education (CHED) on April 30, 2007 issued at San Fernando City, La Union. The
Ladderized Education Program (LEP) was then formally started during the first
semester of SY 2007-2008 with PC Operations NC II as its initial program.

         In the same year, the institute became a college because of the increase
in enrolment.

         On September 17, 2007, DMMMSU ICS was accredited as Competency
Assessment Center for PC Operations NC II with Accreditation No. RO10703154
and Computer Hardware Servicing NC II with Accreditation No. RO10703155.

         The BS Computer Science program had its Preliminary Survey Visit on
December 1 – 3, 2003 and was able to obtain a “Good” Rating for Level I with a
Grand Mean of 3.11. On December 15–17, 2004, the BSCS program had its

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 4]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
Formal Survey Visit by AACCUP and was rated very high in all the areas with a
Grand Mean of 3.33 for Level II (Accredited).

         On February 4-6, 2008, the 2nd Survey Visit for BSCS Program was rated
“Very Good” in all the areas with a Grand Mean of 3.63 for Level II Re-
accredited.

         On August 15-17, 2013, the 3rd Survey Visit (Level III, Phase I) for the
BSCS Program was evaluated “Very Good” with a grand mean of 4.17.

         The college again submits its program for Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation
Survey Visit confident that it can demonstrate the ability to produce educational
outcomes that are consistent with its goals and objectives.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 5]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

              VISION, MISSION, GOALS AND OBJECTIVES

VISION OF DMMMSU
A premiere and globally competitive university
MISSION OF DMMMSU
Provide relevant quality instruction, research and extension
GOALS OF THE COLLEGE OF COMPUTER SCIENCE

      1. To develop quality resources to serve the needs of the information and
           communication technology industry in both national and global labor
           markets;

      2. To share its resources for the educational, cultural, socio-economic, and
           moral upliftment of the people; and

      3. To establish inter-institutional and inter-agency linkages for effective
           implementation of best practices in instruction, research and extension.

OBJECTIVES OF THE COMPUTER SCIENCE PROGRAM
      1. To develop personal, interpersonal. and technical skills thus producing
           holistic and globally competitive IT professionals;
      2. To empower IT graduates to become effective agents of change;
      3. To discover new knowledge and expand existing ones in information
           technology through the conduct of research;
      4. To improve the quality of education through production and use of
           instructional materials;
      5. To lead in promoting and sustaining computer literacy in its service
           areas.
      6. To uplift the lives of Filipino people through community outreach and
           extension services; and
      7. To support and sustain green technology to conserve environment.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 6]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

          NARRATIVE PROFILE

Program:  Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
Areas :
          1. Instruction
          2. Extension
          3. Research
          4. Faculty Development

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 7]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                    INSTRUCTION

         The Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (BSCS) curriculum
complies with the minimum CHED standards in terms of the total number of units
as required by CHED Memorandum Order No. 53, Series of 2006. The curricular
program has a total of 170 units, which exceeds the minimum 155 units. Out of
the 170 units, 74 units are general education courses and NSTP; 84 units are
core, professional and elective computer science courses; 6 units of thesis
writing and 6 units of internship. Furthermore, CHED requires at least 162 hours
of On-the-Job Training/Internship; however, the college requires all intern
students to complete 240 hours.

         The curriculum is relevant since it is science and technology-oriented
attuned to the mission, vision, goals and objectives of the college. It is also
research-oriented because a thesis output is required for the completion of the
program. Graduates of the BSCS program are expected to become applications
developer, computer science instructor, database administrator/designer,
information security engineer, quality assurance engineer, researcher, system
developer, system analyst, and the like.

1. WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES

         The Objectives of the BS Computer Science Program are congruent to the
different national and local goals such as the following:

Philippine Development Plan for 2011-2016

         The Philippine Development Plan for 2011-2016 focuses on the promotion
of global competitiveness and innovation in the Industry and Services sectors.
The government aims at improving the business climate, promoting an
environment that increases productivity and innovative capacity, enforcing
regulations that enhance consumer welfare, and expanding market access. To
achieve this, one of its strategies includes harnessing science, technology, and
innovation (strategy 3).

         The College of Computer Science aims to produce ICT professionals
equipped with personal, interpersonal, and technical skills needed by the industry
and services sectors. It desires to continually improve the quality of education. It
strives to boost the faculty members to produce instructional materials and
innovations in delivering instructions so that students are inspired and motivated
to learn. Moreover, the BSCS program believes that there is knowledge yet to be
discovered in information and communications technology and this could be
attained through the continuous conduct of research. Faculty and students are
greatly involved in the research activity and ensure that these are aligned with
the research agenda of the college and the university.

         The College likewise has scholarship programs to mobilize students
towards learning ICT. It is also committed in founding a solid relationship with the
community through community outreach programs promoting computer literacy.

         Not only does the college cater to the secular learning but it also gives
importance to environmental sustainability. The college is engaged in the
celebration of Earth Day in the community and one of the most common activities
associated are tree planting and coastal cleaning. The college is an advocate of
Green Technology. As a start, the college practices paperless office which

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 8]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

increases the college’s efficiency and it streamlines internal processes. Also, the
dutiful implementation of electricity conservation is everyone’s responsibility in
the college.

National Higher Education Research Agenda (NHERA) Goals 2009-2018

         The 2009-2018 National Higher Education Research Agenda (NHERA)
Goals envision to develop high level and globally competitive workforce, as well
as generate/transfer knowledge and technology for enhancing productivity and
quality of life in order to reduce poverty and ensure sustainable development in
the country.

         These goals are supported by the BSCS curricular program by honing ICT
professionals according to the needed specifications of the industry through the
provision of relevant specializations integrated in its program. In this way,
graduates under the program become holistic professionals providing computing
solutions to the community.

CHED Strategic Plan 2011-2016

         Moreover, the sectoral goal of the 2011-2016 CHED Strategic Plan
concentrates on the formation of highly competitive professional contributing to
national development and generation; and the adaptation and transfer of
knowledge/technology towards national development and global
competitiveness. The program also corroborates with these goals as reflected in
its advocacy in its provision of world-class technology to be utilized in the training
of students in preparation of their deployment in the ICT industry and in its
service areas as system developers and analysts. This is implemented I the
program through the continuing upgrade and maintenance of equipment,
facilities, as well as the courses which met the standards set by the Commission
on Higher Education.

DOST Philippine Digital Strategy

         The Philippine Digital Strategy initiated by the Department of Science and
Technology envisions “a digitally empowered, innovative, globally competitive
and prosperous society where everyone has reliable, affordable and secure
information access in the Philippines as well as a government that practices
accountability and excellence to provide responsive online citizen-centered
services and a thriving knowledge economy through public-private partnership.”

         The program adheres to empowering the members of the community to be
digitally competent in the pursuit of a secure, accurate and reliable exchange of
information through the conduct of extension activities such as Computer
Literacy Training Programs aside from the instruction being delivered to students
during classroom discussions. In this way, the college is able to establish
linkages to organizations which help augment the computing needs of the latter
and satisfying the objective of the college in providing relevant ICT services to
the community.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

DMMMSU Strategic Plan 2011-2015

         In the DMMMSU Strategic Plan (2011-2015), one of the institutional goals
is concentrated on educational development which specifically aims to (1) ensure
effective and efficient educational programs’ implementation with measurable
impacts in the field; (2) ensure equitable distribution of scholarship opportunities
particularly to the underserved and disadvantaged groups; and (3) promote
systematic coordinate physical fitness and sports development activities in the
province.

         In line with this, the program fortifies the students’ educational background
which enables them to contribute to the community along their field of
specialization. Furthermore, the program supports students’ development
through trainings and seminars which is open to deserving students regardless of
their social stature. Aside from industry-related trainings and programs, the
program also supports the physical well-being of students through the conduct of
sports activities.

         The College of Computer Science of Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State
University - South La Union Campus (DMMMSU-SLUC) aims to develop quality
resources to serve the needs of the information and communication technology
industry in both national and global markets; to share its resources for the
educational, cultural, socio-economic and moral upliftment of the people; and to
establish inter-institutional and inter-agency linkages for effective implementation
of best practices in instruction, research, and extension. The BSCS program
embraces its program CMO as its guiding principle in the formulation of its
objectives. The program focuses on the development and empowerment of IT
graduates as reflected on its objectives:

          To develop personal, interpersonal, and technical skills thus producing
             holistic and globally competitive Information and Communications
             Technology (ICT) professionals;

          To empower ICT graduates to become effective agents of change;
          To discover new knowledge and expand existing ones in information

             and communications technology through the conduct of research;
          To improve the quality of education through production and use of

             instructional materials;
          To be committed in uplifting the lives of Filipino people through

             community reach out and extension services; and
          To lead in promoting and sustaining computer literacy in its service

             areas;
          To support and sustain green technology to conserve the environment.

         These objectives are products of the collaboration of students, parents,
alumni, community representatives, linkages, faculty members, and
administration and it is being continually fine-tuned to address the changing
needs of the digital society. The BSCS program aims to produce ICT
professionals equipped with personal, interpersonal and technical skills -- an ICT
professional embodying these characteristics to become agents of change.

         The BSCS program also believes that there is knowledge yet to be
discovered and produced in information and communications technology and this
could be attained through the continuous conduct of research. Faculty and
students are greatly involved in the research activity and ensure that these are
aligned with the research agenda of the college and the university.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 10]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Most importantly, the goals of the BSCS program cannot be realized
without a solid relationship with the community. The college is committed in its
community outreach programs to uplift the lives of the people in its service areas.
Equally important is the desire of the college to continually improve the quality of
education. It strives to boost the faculty members to produce instructional
materials and new innovations in delivering instructions so that students are
inspired and motivated to learn.

2. ADEQUATE AND RELEVANT PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES TO ACHIEVE THE
    OBJECTIVES

         To achieve the objectives of the College of Computer Science, the
following activities and projects are implemented:

2.1.To develop personal, interpersonal and technical skills thus producing holistic
and globally competitive IT professionals; and (2.2.) To empower IT graduates to
become effective agents of change;

Implementing the Policies and Standards of CHED Curriculum for ITE
Programs

         The Curriculum of the Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
(BSCS – Straight Curriculum and Ladderized Education Program) of Don
Mariano Marcos Memorial State University (DMMMSU) was designed and
organized based on the guidelines of the CHED Memorandum Order No.
53 Series of 2006 and CHED Memorandum Order No. 18, Series of 2008.
The adherence of the college to the standards imposed by CHED aims to
train students to be proficient in the design and development of IT
solutions congruent to the needs of both global and national labor
markets. Other relevant IT subjects were also integrated in the curriculum
for the aforementioned purpose making the total number of course offering
units of the college 170 in comparison of the minimum requirements of
CHED which is 155 units as shown in Table 1.

Table 1.Comparison of the existing BSCS curriculum with the CHED standards

                                                                          UNITS

                                     COURSES                   CMO 53,    Existing BSCS
                                                               Series of   Curriculum
A. General Education
      1. Languages and Humanities                                2006
             a. English
             b. Filipino                                                   24 27
             c. Humanities                                     9 12
      2. Mathematics, Natural Sciences and Technology          66
             a. Mathematics                                    99
             b. Natural Sciences
             c. Electives                                                  15 15
      3. Social Sciences and Communications                                              6
             a. Psychology                                                               6
             b. Sociology                                                                3
             c. Anthropology
             d. Economics (with taxation and agrarian reform)              15 18
             e. Philippine History and Culture                                           3
             f. Life and Works of Rizal
             g. Asian/Western Civilization                                       3
             h. Mass Communication                                               3
                                                                                 3

                                                                                 3

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 11]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                                                                   UNITS

                                     COURSES                            CMO 53,         Existing BSCS
                                                                        Series of        Curriculum
             i. Society and Culture (with family planning)
             j. Politics and Governance (with Philippine Constitution)    2006
B. Basic CS Core Courses
      1. Computer Concepts & Fundamentals                                                 3
      2. Computer Programming 1
      3. Professional Ethics in IT                                                  18                 18
      4. Discrete Structure                                             3                 3
      5. Computer Programming 2                                         3                 3
      6. Computer Organization & Assembly Language                      3                 3
C. CS Professional Courses                                              3                 3
      1. Data Structures & Algorithm                                    3                 3
      2. Design & Analysis of Algorithms                                3                 3
      3. Object-Oriented Programming
      4. PC Troubleshooting 1                                                       39                 45
      5. Differential & Integral Calculus                               3                 3
      6. Database Management Systems                                    3                 3
      7. Programming Languages                                          3                 3
      8. PC Troubleshooting 2                                                             3
      9. Automata & Language Theory                                     3                 3
      10. Web Programming                                               3                 3
      11. Digital Design                                                3                 3
      12. Modeling & Simulation                                                           3
      13. Network Principles & Programming                              3                 3
      14. Software Engineering                                          3                 3
      15. Operating Systems                                             3                 3
D. CS Electives                                                         3                 3
      1. File Processing                                                3                 3
      2. Compiler Design                                                3                 3
      3. Computer Graphics                                              3                 3
      4. Office Application and Internet
E. Free Electives                                                                   12                 12
      1. Presentation Skills in IT                                      3                 3
      2. Introduction to Financial Accounting                           3                 3
      3. Multimedia Systems                                             3                 3
F. Physical Education                                                   3                 3
      1. Physical Fitness
      2. Individual and Dual Sports                                                  9                  9
      3. Dances                                                         3                 3
      4. Team Sports                                                    3                 3
G. National Service Training Program                                    3                 3
      1. NSTP 1
      2. NSTP 2                                                                      8                  8
H. Thesis                                                               2                 2
      1. Thesis Writing A                                               2                 2
      2. Thesis Writing B                                               2                 2
I. Practicum                                                            2                 2

                                                       TOTAL UNITS                   6                  6
                                                                        3                 3
                                                                        3                 3

                                                                                     6                  6
                                                                        3                 3
                                                                        3                 3

                                                                                     3                  6

                                                                              155               170

Revision of the Curriculum

         The college ensures that its program strictly adheres to the
objectives, policies, and standards provided by CHED. Hence, there is
periodic review, update, and enhancement of the curricula and syllabi.

         The college involves stakeholders in its curriculum enrichment.
Throughout its operation, the BSCS curriculum has undergone three (3)
revisions. The need for revision was based from the feedbacks of
stakeholders, the employability of graduates as reflected in the institutions’
graduate tracer, and the recommendations of AACCUP accreditors during
the previous visit. Enrichments and revisions were presented to the
college’s academic council and stakeholders, campus’ academic council,
and finally, to the University Academic Council. The University Board of
Regents then passed resolution approving the enrichments/revisions the

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 12]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

latest of which was made last SY 2013 in response to the needs of the
Information Technology Business Process Outsourcing (IT-BPO) industry
as per CMO 34 s 2012.

         Table 2 shows the proposed curricular enrichment for BSCS
integrating the specialization track on Service Management (CMO 34
series of 2012).The enrichment proposal was already presented in the
University Academic Council and compliance to CHED requirements is
underway which includes training of faculty in Service Management
Program (SMP) and establishing partnership with target IT-BPO industry
in the region. Selected faculty members were already sent for SMP
training last May and June 2014. IT Business Processing Association of
the Philippines (IBPAP) coordinates with the DMMMSU in identifying and
establishing the possible industry partners in the region.

         The college also conducts periodic review and updating/enrichment
of course syllabi. The dean, the department chair, and the instruction
facilitator closely review the syllabi and monitor its implementation through
checking of the syllabi, class observations, checking of table of
specifications and test instruments, accomplishment reports, and regular
faculty meetings. In-service trainings are also conducted to continually
update the faculty about the proper preparation of these academic
documents.

Table 2.Enriched BSCS curriculum integrating the specialization track on Service

Management

COURSES                                                              CMO 34 S 2012   Proposed
                                                                                    Enrichments

I. General Education Courses                                         24             24
      A. Languages and Humanities                                    9              9
             1. English
                    a. ENG101 - Study and Thinking Skills            6              6
                    b. ENG102 - Communications for IT
                    c. ENG104 - Technical and Scientific Writing     9              9
             2. Filipino
                    a. FIL101 – Komunikasyon saAkademikong Filipino  15             15
                    b. FIL102 - Pagbasa at Pagsulat tungo sa         6              6
                           Pananaliksik
             3. Humanities
                    a. LIT101 - Literatures of the Philippines
                    b. HUM101 - Art Appreciation and Aesthetics
                    c. PHILO101 - Logic
      B. Mathematics, Natural Sciences and Technology
             1. Mathematics

                    a. MATH101A - College Algebra                    6              6
                    b. MATH102 - Plane Trigonometry                  3              3
             2. Natural Sciences                                     15             15
                    a. CHEM101A - General and Inorganic Chemistry
                    b. PHYS101A - General Physics                    18             18
             3. Electives                                                           3
                    a. STAT101 - Probability and Statistics                         3
      C. Social Sciences and Communications                                         3
             1. RIZAL - Life and Works of Rizal
             2. PSYCH101 - General Psychology with HIV, AIDS and
                    Drug Education
             3. ECON101 - Basic Economics with Taxation and
                    Agrarian Reform
             4. SOCIO101 - Society and Culture with Family Planning
                    and Population Education
             5. POLSCI101 - Politics and Governance with Philippine
                    Constitution
II. Basic CS Core Courses
      1. CS101 - CS Fundamentals
      2. CS102 - Computer Programming 1
      3. CS103 - Computer Programming 2

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 13]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                 COURSES                          CMO 34 S 2012   Proposed
                                                                                 Enrichments
      4. CS104 - Discrete Structures                                         39
      5. CS105 - Computer Organization and Assembly Language                               3
      6. CS106 - Professional Ethics                                                       3
III. CS Professional Courses                                                               3
      1. CS201 - Data Structures                                                          39
      2. CS202 - Design and Analysis of Algorithm
      3. CS203 - Programming Languages                                                     3
      4. CS204 - Automata and Language Theory                                              3
      5. CS205 - Modeling and Simulation                                                   3
      6. CS206 - Digital Design                                                            3
      7. CS207 - Operating Systems                                                         3
      8. CS208 - Network Principles and Programming                                        3
      9. CS209 - Calculus                                                                  3
      10. CS210 - Object Oriented Programming                                              3
      11. CS211 - Database Systems                                                         3
      12. CS212 - Web Programming                                                          3
      13. CS213 - Software Engineering                                                     3
                                                                                           3
IV. CS Electives (CMO No. 18, series of 2008)                            12                3
      1. CS301 - CS Elective 1 (Artificial Intelligence)                                  12
      2. CS302 - CS Elective 2 (Operating Systems: Configuration          9                3
             and Use)                                                                      3
      3. CS303 - CS Elective 3 (Network: Configuration and Use)          21
      4. CS304 - CS Elective 4 (Mobile Computing)                         3                3
                                                                          3                3
V. Free Electives (CMO No. 18, series of 2008)                            3                9
      1. CS401 - Free Elective 1 (Human Computer Interaction)             3                3
      2. CS402 - Free Elective 2 (IT Project Management)                  3                3
      3. CS403 - Free Elective 3 (Graphics and Visualization)     6 (600 hours)            3
                                                                          8               21
VI. Service Management (CMO No. 34, series of 2012)                                        3
      1. SMBUSCO - Business Communication                                 6                3
      2. SMSVCCU - Service Culture                                                         3
      3. SMFBPO1 - Fundamentals of Business Processes                     6
             Outsourcing 101                                                               3
      4. SMFBPO2 - Fundamentals of Business Processes
             Outsourcing 102                                                               3
      5. SMSYSTH - Principles of Systems Thinking                                 6 (600 hours)
      6. SMINTRN – Internship
                                                                                           8
VII. Physical Education                                                                    2
      1. PE101 - Fundamentals of Physical Fitness                                          2
      2. PE102 - Individual and Dual Sports                                                2
      3. PE103 - Dances                                                                    2
      4. PE104 - Team Sports                                                               6
                                                                                           3
VIII. National Service Training Program                                                    3
      1. NSTP101                                                                           6
      2. NSTP102                                                                           3
                                                                                           3
IX. Thesis
      1. CS501 - Thesis 1                                                            173
      2. CS502 - Thesis 2

TOTAL UNITS                                                       173

IBPAP representatives and DMMMSU officials and heads regularly meet to discuss
Service Management Program for IT-BPO as integral part of the BSCS, BSIT and BSIS
curricular programs.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 14]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Qualification of Faculty Members

         The college aims to strengthen its faculty workforce because they
are the forefront of its mandate in instruction. Faculty members are
encouraged to pursue graduate studies relevant to its program. Currently,
the dean of the college is a Master in Computer Science (MCS) and a
Doctor in Information Technology (DIT) degree holder. The chairpersons
of the straight and ladderized departments are Master in Information
Technology (MIT) degree holders with relevant administrative experience.
Majority of the faculty workforce are MIT degree holders. There are also
faculty members with allied degree courses such as Master in Information
System, Master in Engineering Major in Electronics and Communications
Engineering and Doctor of Education Major in Math. To further boost their
professional and academic competencies, faculty members also attend to
trainings, seminars, conferences and conventions, both in local and global
venues. Faculty members also hold several relevant eligibilities and
certifications such as Computer Hardware Servicing NC II, Programming
NC IV, Assessor and Trainer Qualifications (AQTQ), Open-source
certifications, CSC professional eligibility, and PRC Board license.

Highest Degree Earned

                                 3%  DIT
19% 7%                               DIT w/units
                                     MIT/MIS/MCS/MA
                          71%        MIT/MCS -w/units

                            Figure 1.Educational attainment of faculty members

         Conduct of Regular Classes

                  The college implements the 18-week requirement for each course
         during a semester. Other activities are scheduled in accordance to the
         University Academic Calendar being prepared for each year by the
         University Academic Council to ensure that the standard requirement is
         met. Core and professional computer science courses are conducted at
         least two hours per week of lecture session and at least 3 hours of
         laboratory session. With this, students acquire the essential knowledge of
         the course during the lecture classes and develop skills and competencies
         through enrichment activities during laboratory classes. In addition, the
         department chairman conducts periodic observation of classes to make

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 15]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         certain that the appropriate instruction is provided to the students of the
         college based on the course syllabi (see Appendix B and C).

         Extra-Curricular Activities

                  Other than honing the skills of CCS students through classroom-
         contained instructions, the college also involves them in activities which
         aim to expose them to collaborative, competitive, and social environments
         to ensure their total development. These activities are as follows:
         1. Sports Olympics held annually to select the best players to represent

             the college in the upcoming sports events. This also encourages
             students to be physically active and alert thus improving their well-
             being.
         2. Cultural Activities which includes the conduct of annual Mr. and Ms.
             CCS and the putting up of the Performing Arts and Creative Society
             which aims to hone the artistic potentials of the students to the fullest.
         3. Conduct of the annual Quiz Bowl and Skills Competition by the
             institutional organization called the Computer Science and Technology
             Club (now Coders and Innovators Society) which provide a healthy
             competitive environment to students specializing in Programming,
             Networking, Web Development, Graphics Designing, and other core
             computing skills.
         4. Joining IT-related competitions, specifically, the Annual TESDA
             Provincial Skills Olympics which started in 2009. CCS student
             representatives gave pride to the college for winning as Champion in
             the field of Programming for 3 consecutive years (Justin Bernard
             Fiestada (2009-2010), Jeremias Caras (SY 2010-2011), and Alex
             Enrique (SY 2011-2012)).

         Learning Enrichment

                  Trainings and Seminars. The college provides support to students
         who attend trainings and seminars such as Job Placement Seminar
         Workshop, Web Development Seminar Workshop, PC Troubleshooting
         Seminar Workshop, Y4IT sponsored by PSITE, iLikeIT (Ilocandia Like IT)
         sponsored by Lorma Colleges, City of San Fernando, La Union, Smarter
         ICT Professional for Smarter Philippines sponsored by Smart
         Communications, Graphic Designing and Multimedia Development
         sponsored by Graphika Manila Design Studio, and Drupal Open-source
         Content Management System held at St. Louis University, Baguio City.
         Seminars are also included as part of the syllabi in some General
         Education courses such as Politics and Governance with Philippine
         Constitution, Entrepreneurship and Productivity, and Economics with
         Taxation and Agrarian Reforms.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 16]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

BSCS students during the Graphika Manila 2014 International Multimedia Design
Conference on February 1, 2014 at the SMX Convention Center, MOA Complex,
Pasay City Philippines

BSCS student delegates during the Graphika Manila 2013 Conference held on
February 9, 2013 at PICC Plenary Hall, Roxas Boulevard

                  Learner-Centered Instruction. Appropriate teaching
         methodologies are being considered in the syllabi enrichment. These
         include, but not limited to, cooperative learning, peer teaching, group
         dynamics, case/project study, brainstorming, micro-teaching, macro-
         teaching, multimedia/courseware, reporting, simulations, seminars, and
         film showing (see Appendix B and C).

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 17]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

 The students undergo brainstorming with regards to the topic in their subject
 Professional Ethics in IT as they gather ideas and information from each
 members of the group.
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 18]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Group discussion of students as they devise their strategy on how to come up to a
better performance.

Peer teaching of students in a topic given by their instructor as required by the course.
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 19]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

 Classroom setup that encompasses group discussion or peer teaching of
 students as part of the evaluation measures of the course.
Student Performance Evaluation

                  To assess the knowledge and competency of students on both
         professional and general courses, the following performance evaluation
         tools are being utilized:

                  Practicum/On-the-Job Training. This is a 6-unit course offering of
         the college which exposes students to actual work environment. For
         years, trainees are deployed in local and regional government agencies
         (NEDA, NSO, SSS etc.) and private agencies (ULPI, PNB, MetroBank
         etc.). The scope of the trainees’ duty and other agreements are covered in
         the Memorandum of Agreement issued by the college prior to the
         internship. This training also gives students perceptions on how the real
         world operates through the services they provide and exercise work
         ethics. This activity aims to develop the students’ independence,
         competence, and social values. The final grade of the student-trainees is
         determined based on the performance as evaluated by their immediate
         supervisor and OJT faculty-coordinator. In the computation of the final
         grade, sixty percent (60%) comes from the immediate supervisor and forty
         percent (40%) from the OJT faculty-coordinator. Upon completion of the
         training, the student trainees submit to the OJT coordinator a narrative
         report, peer evaluation forms, and evaluation sheets from the agency (see
         Appendix F).

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 20]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                     Students Participation in the
                       On-the-Job Training 2014

                                               Private
                                                 25%
                                                             Government
                                                                  75%

             Figure 2. Distribution of Students in the Summer 2014 OJT
                  Hands-on Laboratory Activities. The core, professional, and

         elective computer science courses being offered in the college include 54
         hours of laboratory and workshop classes (except Professional Ethics in
         IT, Design and Analysis of Algorithm, Automata and Language Theory,
         and Discrete Structure) which allow students to perform practical
         applications of the computing technologies discussed during the lecture
         class.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 21]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  BSCS students as they perform laboratory activities.
                  Case Studies. This technique focuses on the development of
         output during laboratory classes in the form of programs, systems,
         models, graphic designs and others as requirement for the subject. This
         aims to familiarize students with the environment and the use of the
         different software being used.

          A model of an infrastructure generated using a Free Modelling Software.
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 22]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

              3D rendering of Facial Features using a Face Generation Modeller

                  Examination/Test. To measure the efficacy of the teaching and
         learning process, the following evaluation techniques are being
         implemented:

                  a. Written Examination. This includes activities such as quizzes,
                      exercises, and homework/assignments which evaluate the skills
                      of students. Two major examinations in every subject are being
                      administered by instructors per semester. The items given in
                      these major examinations are guided by the table of
                      specifications prepared by subject instructors.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 23]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
                  b. Oral Examination. To assess the communication skills of
                      students and their proficiency in the subject matters being
                      discussed, oral examinations in the form of mock interviews,
                      oral presentations, and class recitations are done. Likewise,
                      high-level questions are being raised by instructors to test the
                      critical thinking and mastery of students in a particular
                      topic/output.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 24]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
                  c. Laboratory Examination. Aside from written examinations,
                      subject instructors also administer hands-on evaluation dealing
                      with the use of software and IT concepts. Networked
                      examination software is being used to integrate objective type
                      items which deal with IT concepts. A rubric is also being used to
                      measure the competency of each student in a particular
                      laboratory examination.

         Graduate Tracer System
                 The College of Computer Science utilizes an Online Graduate

         Tracer System developed and maintained by the college MIS facilitator.
         Core faculty members headed by Ms. Agnes Suguitan currently conduct a
         study entitled “Graduate Tracer Study of CCS, DMMMSU-SLUC” to
         assess whether the institution provides relevant instruction and training to
         students in accordance to the needs of the stakeholders, particularly the
         computing industry and community. The online tracer system
         automatically generates statistics and charts summarizing the data from
         the graduates/alumni. This serve as basis for curriculum enrichment and
         improvements to keep pace with the demands of the industry.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 25]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Figure 3. The online graduate tracer system developed by the MIS facilitator of
             the college

Employability of Graduates

         The College of Computer Science aims to empower its students to
become globally competitive ICT professionals through the provision of industry-
related knowledge, skills, and training and this is attained as shown by the
graduates employed in the different private and public institutions with roles
vertically articulated with their specializations.

         The monitoring of graduates is made through an online graduate system
developed by the college’s MIS facilitator. Accumulated responses show that
most of the CCS graduates from 2012-2014 are employed.

Graduates Employability Rate

300 248 285 263

200                                      54              114
                                               50%              88%
                        82
100                                Year 2013        Year 2014

                              70%

   0
                 Year 2012

Number of Graduates
Number of Graduates Employed Related to Specialization
Percentage of Graduates Employed

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 26]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         In 2012, 70% of the 248 graduates are employed 82 of which have jobs
related to their specialization. On the other hand, out of the 285 graduates of the
school year 2013, 50% were able to find a job and 54 of these statistics belong to
industry-related occupation. Latest graduates garnered the highest percentage of
employees with results showing that 88% of the 263 graduates landed
employments - 114 of which are in employed in workplaces related to their
specialization.
2.3. To discover new knowledge and expand existing ones in information
technology through the conduct of research;

         Thesis Writing
                  The curricular program includes a two-semester thesis writing, one

         semester for the presentation of thesis proposal and another semester for
         the final oral defense of the research study. This course requirement
         allows students to participate in the research activities of the college. This
         is focused on the development of computing solutions and other technical
         researches relevant to the IT field. To further encourage students to
         improve the quality of their outputs, an annual Best in Thesis award is
         given to the group of students who excelled in the development of the
         study and the production of quality research manuscript (see Appendix E).

       A group of BSCS fourth year students presents their study during
       their final oral thesis defense
2.4. To improve the quality of education through production and use of
instructional materials;

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 27]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Instructional Materials Development

         Faculty members continually develop and refine instructional
materials for their students in the different courses. In fact, multiple
research studies about needs analysis or assessment for instructional
materials development were conducted and passed during the in -house
reviews in 2013. It has been advised by the administration thatprior to the
development of instructional materials, needs analysis study should be
conducted as a justification for the development of such material. The
module will then be developed and reviewed by a technical team during
another campus in-house review. Copyrighted materials developed by
faculty members are as follows:

Instructional            Title               Date Approved        Subject Where Used
   Material                               June/October 2010-  Employed/Used in all
                                          2013                subjects
A. Syllabi      Employed/Used in all     June/October 2010-  CS 207, CS 101
                                          2013                CS 304, CS 101
               subjects                   June/October 2010-  CS 304, CS 101
                                          2013                CS 304, CS 101
B. Modules  Module in Digital Design     June/October 2010-  CS 304
                                          2013
               by A. Veras                June/October 2010-  CS 402, CS 302
                                          2013
                Module in MS Word 2007   June/October 2010-  CS 304, CS 101
                                          2013                CS 402, CS 403
               by M. Gali                 June/October 2010-
                                          2013                CS 304
                Module in MS Excel 2007
                                          June/October 2010-  Employed / Used in all
               by D. Llavore and I.       2013                Subjects

                   Duran                                      CS 214, CS 215
                Module in MS
                                                              CS 203
                   PowerPoint 2007
                Operating E-mail and

               Search the Web Using

               Browsers

                Advanced Computer

               Skills and Development

               Training Program

               o Photo Editing using

               Adobe Photoshop by

               Veras et.al

               o Desktop Publishing

               using MS Publisher

               by Duran et.al.

               o Creating Animation

               Using Macromedia

               Flash by Dacanay

               et.al

               o Internet Access using

               Web Browsers by

               Meneses et.al

C. Electronic  Powerpoint

Materials      Presentations/CDs,

               DVDs, Films

                A Courseware in PC       June/October 2010-
                   Trouble shooting       2013

                E-learning Courseware    June/October 2010-
                    in OOP                2013

          An example electronic material is the Courseware in PC Troubleshooting
which was developed by a faculty as a supplemental tool in the delivery of
instruction in the PC Troubleshooting course. Some undergraduate theses also
deal with development of instructional materials such as modules, computer-aided
instruction and game-based learning.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 28]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Courseware in PC Troubleshooting developed by Mr. Enrico
Dacanay, Department Chair of the Computer Science Program.

         In addition, the following are the on-going instructional materials which
have been presented during the in-house reviews:

  Instructional                           Title            Year Started  Subject Where
     Material                                                                  Used
                  Workbook in Computer Concepts and
A. Books             Fundamentals by I. Duran              2014          CS 101
B. Modules
                  Module in Computer Programming I        2013          CS 102
C. Worktext
                     by L. Dacaymat, M. Balcita and J.     2014          CS 208
                                                           2014          CS 212
                     Milan
                  Module for Web Programming by H.        2013          CS 209
                                                           2014          CS 209
                     Limson
                  Module in Network Principles and        2013          CS 104
                                                           2014          CS 106
                     Programming by C. Marzan, C.          2013          CS 211

                     Albarillo, M. Baculo, N. De Vera, B.

                     Dungan and E. Munar
                  Worktext in Automata and Language

                     Theory by F. Burgos and E. Munar
                  Worktext in Automata and Language

                     Theory with Java for Formal

                     Language and Automata Package

                     (JFLAP) by F. Burgos and E. Munar
                  Worktext in Discrete Structures by K.

                     Dacanay and E. Dacanay
                  Worktext in Professional Ethics in

                     Information Technology by K.

                     Dacanay and E. Dacanay
                  Worktext in Operating Systems by A.

                     Soria and F. Mendoza

2.5. To lead in promoting and sustaining computer literacy in its service area;

                  Since 2001, the college has extended its service to sustain
         computer literacy in its service areas through its Computer Literacy

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 29]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Training Program (CLTP) and Advanced Computer Skills Development
         Program (ACSDTP). In cooperation with the Local Government Unit (LGU)
         of the Municipality of Agoo and the Office of the Representative of the 2nd
         District of La Union, the college was able to serve public and private
         school teachers and other professionals in La Union such as PNP
         personnel and LGU employees. This partnership program contributed to
         the various literacy programs of the Municipality of Agoo. The LGU
         eventually received in 2009 the renowned UNESCO Confucius Prize for
         Literacy which was awarded in Paris, France.

                  The college also extended its service to the public school pupils of
         the Municipality of Agoo through its Share-a-Ware Program which aims to
         train pupils to become computer literate in order to keep pace with other
         pupils in private schools which are better equipped with IT tools and
         technologies. The college dedicated every Wednesday afternoon where
         faculty and students work together in the computer laboratory to teach the
         invited pupils.

The cooperation of the DMMMSU-SLUC College of Computer Science, Office of
the Municipal Mayor and the Office of the Congressman leads to the success of
the continuing computer literacy programs

2.6. To be committed to uplift the lives of Filipino people through community
reach out and extension services;

                  Aside from the CLTP, Share-a-Ware program and the ACSDTP,
         the college annually adopts a barangay where the faculty members,
         student facilitators and the administrators share livelihood seminars which
         target the well-being and development of the out-of-school youth and
         unemployed citizens in the said communities. Seminars include livelihood
         topics such as Bangus Deboning, Puto with salted egg, Orange Smoothie
         and Chocolate Graham Brittle Bar, Bamboo Shoot Burger, Ham and

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 30]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Cheese Rolls, Special Polvoron, Cookies and Cream, Bangus Roll, Coffee
         Jelly, Leche Flan, Art-making using recycled papers, Personalized Cards,
         Dimsum Delight, Homemade Longganisa, Gracilaria Kroepeck Making,
         and many others. Other topics include tax computation, Dangerous Drug
         Act, child psychology, good parenting, things to consider in buying
         computers, family planning, stress management, family code, aerobics,
         taebo, basic life support, household and healthcare and many more.

          BSCS students take part in the extension activities of the college by
          assisting the trainees during the computer literacy training.

2.7. To support and sustain green technology to conserve environment.
                  Austerity Measures. The College of Computer Science imposes

         laboratory rules which aim for the sustainability of the cleanliness and in
         saving the energy consumption of the facilities. The college also employs
         laboratory assistants to ensure that the equipment are working properly
         and are utilized appropriately. The college also implements the university
         policy of proper time of turning on and off of air conditioning units issued
         by the Office of the University President as well as the participation to the
         Earth Day hour.

                  Use of Eco-friendly Equipment. The purchase and utilization of
         energy efficient peripherals and other mechanisms are exercised by the
         institution. The use of laptops instead of desktop computers in offices,
         equipping laboratory rooms with LCD/LED monitors as replacement to the
         old CRT monitors, all-in-one desktop computers in computer laboratory,
         continuous ink system in printers to minimize disposing of ink cartridges,
         and preventive maintenance of computers to prolong the useful life of
         computers in the laboratory.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 31]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  Paperless Examination. Faculty members administer examination
         through a network-based examination system which saves resources
         needed for the printing of the paper- and pencil-based examination. Some
         faculty members allow online submission of homework or projects.

                  A
         u
         t
         o
         m
         a
         t
         e
         d
         a
         n
         d
         Computerized Systems. The Management of Information System of the
         campus headed by a CCS faculty member developed systems such as
         the Online PDS System which provides paperless transaction and
         management of the profile of all employees of the campus. They also
         developed online tool for the submission of accomplishment reports. They
         also developed a graduate tracer system which is found in the campus
         website. The system allows graduates to fill-out information regarding their
         employment status. The system generates statistical reports about the
         graduates. Moreover, dissemination about the system is done through text
         messaging or social networking sites to fast-track the process. Automated
         and computerized systems are even utilized in various extra-curricular
         activities of the college such as voting systems in pageant, random
         selection of questions in quiz bowl, and instant picking of winners in raffle
         draw. These are all intended to minimize the use of paper.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 32]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

3. SYSTEMATIC AND EFFECTIVE PROCEDURES

         Curriculum Development. The enrichment of curricular programs of the
college is governed by university policies and adheres to CHED standards. The
college involves its stakeholders by considering their feedbacks and suggestions.
Proposed revisions are presented in the college academic council for further
scrutiny and refinement. The refined curriculum is then presented to the campus
and university academic council for further refinement. Then the enrichment
proposal is forwarded to CHED for certification that the curriculum enrichment
conforms to the policies and standards. This certification is then attached to the
packaged curriculum enrichment for final approval at the university level by the
Board of Regents.

         Recently, the college subjected its curricular programs (straight and
ladderized programs) for compliance to minimum CHED standards and policies.
The said curricular programs are certified “contents-noted” by CHED and are
now forwarded to central administration for the Board of Regents’ approval of the
revisions. Specialization on Service Management Track for IT-BPO (CMO 34 S
2012) is also being integrated in the computer science curriculum to be submitted
to CHED for a separate certification of contents-notation. This track includes five
additional courses as addendum to the existing courses offered in the program.
This is to further equip BSCS students’ necessary competency skills to meet the
demands of the steadily growing IT-BPO industry, both in local and international
business environment.

         Academic Policies. All academic-related activities are governed by
university policies prescribed in various manuals such as faculty manual,
administrative manual, and student handbook. Academic policies and processes
include academic calendar, admission and retention policies, schedule and
conduct of classes, examinations and grading system, academic honors and
awards, advising, classroom regulations and management, thesis, OJT and
others.

         Teaching Methodology. The faculty members adopt teaching methods
and techniques suited to the courses. Faculty utilizes approaches that would
train, develop, and enhance the analytical, logical and critical thinking skills of
students. The faculty also utilizes the use of technology tools such as computers,
LCD projectors, interactive software, and online resources.

         Faculty Performance Evaluation. Quality of instructional delivery is a
primary responsibility of each faculty member. Thus, faculty members are
evaluated once in a semester to measure their teaching effectiveness. An official
instrument is used to gather data from different groups of respondents. A
significant sample of students and peer faculty members are considered as
respondents along with the immediate supervisor. A self-assessment using the
same instrument is also taken into account. The result of the evaluation is a
reflection of faculty members’ performance and a way to provide them room for
improvements by considering the feedbacks of the respondents involved. Prompt
submission of periodic academic reports is also being monitored by the
immediate supervisor. Class observation is also conducted periodically (see
Appendix A).

         Operational Plans. Each faculty member prepares an operational plan
and faculty development plan to set the goals and objectives aligned with the
VMGO’s and target learning outcomes. The chairpersons also prepare their

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 33]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

operational and supervisory plans dealing with faculty workload, class schedule,
academic reports (syllabi, accomplishment reports, table of specification, test
instruments, report on rating), faculty performance evaluation, and faculty needs.
The dean of the college also prepares operational plan which includes faculty
development plan, procurement plan, and supervisory plan to determine the
priority programs and projects for the college. Different facilitators and other
designations also prepare operational plans in their respective quasi-
assignments. At the end of the term, accomplishment reports are submitted to
determine how far each achieved one’s goals and objectives. With this, one
would be able to improve plans in the future.

4. REASONABLE BUDGET

         Budget Allocation. The University maintains a Financial Management
Office run by qualified and competent personnel and responsible for the efficient
management of financial resources/funds of the college. Concerned faculty, staff,
and officials participate in the preparation of the budget and procurement
program thus, a fair and objective system and budgetary allocation is adopted.
The budget committee reviews, evaluates, and consolidates the Internal
Operating Budgets of the colleges and integrates these to the proposed annual
budget of the college. For the budget preparation and allocation, it needs to
prepare first the estimated budget that is required by the department/unit level
and categorized as research, extension, production, instruction, administration,
and planning. After which, budget requirements will be submitted to the budget
office of the university then it will be forwarded to the Central Office of the
Department of Budget and Management. Once approved, the budget shall be
released based on the work and financial plan of the different operating units.
Finally, sub-allotments to pay obligation within approved appropriations like Fund
101 (General Fund) and Fund 164 (Special Trust Fund) will be made.

         Fund Releases. The college provides a specific budgetary allotment for
the following:

          Purchase of instructional equipment facilities, supplies, and materials
          Conduct of research activities, extension, and community service
          Improvement of library holdings/service/facilities
          Repair and maintenance of physical facilities and laboratories
          Faculty and staff development
          Faculty and staff incentives and benefits

         The college allocates the trust funds for the following services and
activities:

          Cultural Development
          Sports Development
          Medical/Dental
          Library
          Student Body Organization
          Guidance and Counseling Services

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 34]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

5. PROVISION OF MATERIALS AND OTHER RESOURCES

         The college sees to it that there are adequate materials and resources to
meet the needs of its program.

         Faculty Profile. The college has a strong faculty profile in terms of
educational qualification, experience, academic rank, trainings and seminars,
relevant eligibilities and certifications, membership to professional organizations.
Hiring and selection policy requires at least a relevant Master’s degree, teaching
experience and research-oriented. The administration which includes the dean
and chairpersons boosts of relevant graduate degrees and experience. Likewise,
majority of the faculty members hold relevant graduate degrees and experiences.
Through its faculty development plan, the college continually provides each
faculty member with opportunities towards professional growth and development.

         Physical Plants and Facilities. The college has sufficient classrooms to
accommodate 34 sections. The classroom size met the standard specifications
for learning activities. The college has seven laboratory rooms and 22 lecture
rooms. The classrooms are well-lighted and ventilated. These are maintained
and kept clean through the cooperation of the faculty members, staff,and
students. The laboratories are air-conditioned and equipped with the advanced
materials and equipment needed by the courses offered. Also, the rooms have
additional electric fans, projector screen, whiteboards, and cabinets. Additional
laboratory rooms, a state-of-the-art audio-visual room, and networked
infrastructure are also underway. The current facility of the college, especially the
multi-purpose hall is already inspected by the University President and VP for
Planning and a proposal is being prepared to transform it into a 2-storey building
to house additional classrooms and offices.

         Instructional Materials. Every faculty is encouraged to produce
instructional materials for the teaching and learning environment. Thus, many
faculty researches involve instructional materials development in various core
and professional courses to cater the needs of the students. Needs assessments
of instructional materials were already done in some courses and the next phase
which is development and validation is already on-going. Proper development
and validation process is done in the form research activity to ensure its quality
before its utilization. Likewise, approval from the campus review committee shall
be undertaken before utilization of the IMs.

         Library Services. In order to have a well-organized and quality utilization
of the library as well as providing efficient and effective services rendered, the
library is available from 7:00 am to 6:00 pm, Monday to Friday for undergraduate
students and from 8:00 am to 5:00 pm for graduate students. The library is
accessible during lunch break implementing the “No Noon Break” Policy.
Librarians and staff are available during library hours to assist and provide
services to users. The library adopts a system which is the Automated Library
System (developed by Mr. Jerome P. Songcuan, a CCS faculty member) which
provides faculty, students and other users greater access to the library collection
and services. In addition, the library promotes and disseminates its program
through a regular announcement of its new acquisitions, resources, facilities and
services.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 35]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Scholarships/Study Leave. The administration is supportive to faculty
members who desire to attend seminars, trainings, conferences and to avail
scholarships and study leave. There were two (2) faculty members who already
availed the university scholarship and graduated as Doctor in Information
Technology while one has still on-going and on a study-leave for dissertation in
Doctor in Information Technology. Many faculty members are also benefited by
the Thesis and Dissertation aids provided by the university.

         Student Services. The Office of the Student Affairs and Services (OSAS)
offers services and programs that are concerned with non-academic experiences
of students to attain total student development. Under the supervision of the
University Director of Student Affairs and Services, it provides an array of
services devoted to serving the studentry to ensure that the living and learning
environments help students attain their academic goals. Non-academic services
are two pronged: those that relate to student welfare and those that relate to
student development.

          Student Welfare Services. These are basic services and programs
             that promote and ensure students’ well-being. It includes the following:
                   Guidance and Counseling
                   Scholarship
                   Financial Assistance
                   Mutual Aid
                   Testing Service
                   Career Guidance and Placement Services
                   Student Housing
                   Medical and Dental Services
                   Alumni Relations
                   Admission and Records
                   Food Services
                   Library Services

          Student Development Programs and Services. These are designed
             for the exploration, enhancement, and development of the student’s full
             potential for personal development, leadership, and social
             responsibility through various institutions and student-initiated
             activities. It includes the following:
                   Student Organization
                   Student Discipline
                   Spiritual Programs
                   Cultural Development
                   Sports Development
                   Student Publication

6. PARTICIPATION OF SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF
    FACULTY/STAFF/STUDENTS/COMMUNITY IN MAJOR
    PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES

         Orientation for New Students. The orientation for BSCS Freshmen and
Transferees is conducted two or three weeks after the start of classes. The
students are informed about the university and college rules and regulations,
scholarships/grants available, student services offered, and functions of the

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 36]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

different offices. Moreover, the faculty members and staff are introduced during
the first day of classes and during the acquaintance party.

         Involvement in Curriculum Development. Faculty members, students,
alumni, and a representative from an industry are involved in the curriculum
revision and development of the Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
program. The curriculum development is governed by university policies and
CHED standards; certified “contents-noted” by CHED. The final approval of the
revisions is done by the Board of Regents. Specialization on Service
Management Track for IT-BPO (CMO 34, s. 2012) is also being integrated in the
computer science curriculum.

         Involvement in Research. The BSCS students are required to conduct a
thesis in system development or in social research as a requirement of the
program. The student researchers need to present and defend their output orally
to competent panel members from the college professors/instructors and a
representative from the institution where the system development was
implemented who serves as an external evaluator. Furthermore, the BSCS
faculty members are required to produce a research at least once a year and it
must be presented orally in the campus/university in-house review. These
research outputs are published in the college’s research journal. Faculty
members are encouraged to present their researches in the international and
national conventions. Recently, there were five faculty members who presented
their researches internationally, two (2) faculty members presented in a national
convention, and two (2) presented in a regional convention. The college has its
research journal where faculty members and students publish their researches
and researched-based articles (see Appendix D and E).

         Extension and Community Involvement Activities. The college is
committed to cater the needs and services of the community specifically in the
Municipality of Agoo and expanded its service in the Second District of La Union.
It adopts a barangay from the Municipality of Agoo and offers computer literacy
and outreach programs, renders computer literacy training program and
advanced computer skills development training program for the public school
teachers and employees of the Municipality of Agoo and Second District of La
Union. The administration, faculty, staff, and students are involved in the
implementation of the college’s extension and community involvement activities.

         Projects/Activities. The faculty and students of the BSCS program are
involved in the planning, preparation, and implementation of the different
activities of the college as follows:

         a. Sports Olympics held annually to select the best players to represent
             the college in the upcoming sports events. This also encourages
             students to be physically active and alert, thus, improving their well-
             being.

         b. Cultural Activities which include the conduct of annual Mr. and Ms.
             CCS and the putting up of the Performing Arts and Creative Society
             which aims to hone the artistic potentials of the students to the fullest.
             The selected students represent the college during different cultural
             activities in the campus level and university level as well as in the
             regional and national levels.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 38]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 39]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

            c. Conduct of the annual Quiz Bowl and Skills Competition organized
                 by the recognized student organization called the Computer Science
                 and Technology Club (now Coders and Innovators Society) which
                 provide a healthy competitive environment to students specializing
                 in Programming, Networking, Web Development, Graphics
                 Designing and other core computing skills.

            d. Joining IT-related competitions, specifically, the Annual TESDA
                 Provincial Skills Olympics which started on 2009. CCS student
                 representatives gave pride to the college for winning as Champion in
                 the field of Programming for 3 consecutive years (Justin Bernard
                 Fiestada (2009-2010), Jeremias Caras (SY 2010-2011), and Alex
                 Enrique (SY 2011-2012)).

7. AWARDS OF DISTINCTION AND ACHIEVEMENTS AND GRANTS OF
    THIS PROGRAM

           Grants/Scholarships of the Program. The college offers scholarship,
    assistantship, and financial assistance program to deserving students for
    educational purposes. To expand the beneficiaries of scholarship grants, the
    program also scouts for possible private grantors to deserving students. The
    following are the scholarship and educational grants offered to students:

            Entrance Scholarship for Freshmen Entering College
                    o Full Scholarship for Valedictorian from public and private high
                         schools or gold medalist in the regional athletics, cultural and
                         academic competitions
                    o Partial Scholarship for Salutatorian from public and private
                         high schools or silver medalist in the regional athletics, cultural
                         and academic competitions),

            Academic Scholarship (Full/Partial Scholarship)
            Students with Special Talents (Athletics, Cultural, Student Publication

               and Special Skill/Abilities/Talents)
            University Student Council
            Student with Leadership Capabilities
            NSTP - ROTC Corps Commander, and
            Dependents of permanent employees of the university.

             Furthermore, there are also other scholarships and grants funded by
    government and private institutions such as:

            Local Code Scholarship
            CHED-Sponsored Scholarship (CHED One-Town-One Scholar

               Program)
            DSWD-Sponsored Scholarship
            St. Benedictine Foundation
            DMMMSU Alumni Association
            DMMMSU Seed 79 Alumni
            Kabataan Party List
            Philex Mining and others.

             As of the first semester of the current school year 2014-2015, there are
    total scholarship grants of 111. In the school year 2013-2014, there are a total
    of 127 scholars and 78 scholars in the first semester and second semester,

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 40]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

    respectively. Majority of the scholarship grants are Local Code and
    government scholarships.

             Award of AACCUP Accrediting Agency. The Bachelor of Science in
    Computer Science Program has been awarded Level III - Phase 1 accredited
    status in the previous accreditation last August 2013. The program was rated
    very high with a grand mean of 4.17 during the last survey visit on August
    2013.

             Practicum/Internship of Students.The BSCS students are required
    to undergo On-the-Job-Training. Recognition is given during commencement
    exercises for those deserving students who have outstanding performance
    and meritorious accomplishments during the training. The following students
    were given award for Best in Practicum: Marivic Garcia (SY 2013-2014),
    Abigail Javier (SY 2012-2013), Rodelbert Lopez (SY 2011-2012) and
    Marishiel Reaño (SY 2010-2011) (see Appendix F).

             Awards/Recognition Received by Faculty. Many faculty members
    are recognized by local, national, and international award giving bodies.
    Some of these are Best Oral Presentation, Best Paper, Graduated with High
    Honors, Service Award, Extension Worker of the Year, Technology of the
    Year and Best Undergraduate Thesis Adviser.

             Awards/Recognition Received by BSCS Students. The college
    recognizes the achievements of students in academics, sports, and cultural
    activities. The following table summarizes the number of BSCS students who
    are recipients of major awards given by the college/university such as
    deserving honor students and special awards from the different intercollegiate
    competitions attended such as SCUAA-1 Olympics, National SCUAA
    Olympics, National Statistics Month Celebration, and National BFAR Fish
    Conservation Week Celebration. The most recent recognition received by a
    student is First Place Winner in the Photo-Editing Category during the
    International Geographic Contest in the person of Romeo Jacaban, a BSCS
    fourth year student, and his adviser is Prof. Sabrina L. Estacio, a CCS faculty
    member.

     Romeo Jacaban’s masterpiece which depicts the resiliency of the Filipino nation.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 41]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

    Romeo Jacaban won 1st Place in Photo-Editing Contest in International
    Geography Contest, London, UK.

A documentary video entitled “Bong-Bong” became national 5thPlacerin Short
Documentary during the Fish Conservation Week Celebration of the Bureau of
Fisheries and Aquatic Resources (BFAR). Romeo Jacaban (upper left), a BSCS
student, produced the documentary video. He is also a national finalist for
producing short documentary entitled “Magturo Na” during the 1000 Teachers
Program by the Philippine Business Education.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 42]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 43]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Summary of major and special awards received by students

         AWARD                            SCHOOL YEAR

                            2013-2014  2012-2013  2011-2012  2010-2011

Magna Cum Laude             2                          12

Cum Laude                   13 10 10                               4

Web Developer of the Year   1          1               1

Programmer of the Year      1                          11

System Analyst of the Year                                         1

Best in Thesis              12 4 4 6

Loyalty Award               3117

Cultural Achievement Award             141

Sports Achievement Award               169

La Union Provincial Skills

Competitions

 Programming               1111

 Graphics Design           1                          1

University Olympics

 Champion                  56 44 47
 1st Runner Up             82

SCUAA 1

 Champion                  53
 1st Runner Up
 2nd Runner Up             17 10 10

                            16 2                       4

National SCUAA Champion                1

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 44]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                     COMPLIANCE REPORT

Extent of Compliance with the Teams’ Recommendations for Area III
(Curriculum and Instruction) in the last survey visit

RECOMMENDATIONS                     ACTION TAKEN                       PERCENTAGE
                                                                               OF REMARKS

                                                                       COMPLIANCE

1. Full compliance to the           The college seeks to comply        75%   On-going
    recommendations in the          fully with the recommendations     100%    Done
    previous survey visit is        in the previous survey visit.
    recommended with                                                   100%    Done
    corresponding pieces of         The college is establishing        100%    Done
    evidence.                       linkages with other learning
                                    institutions.
Recommendations during 2nd
Survey Visit:                       Instructional materials
                                    development in the college is
     a. The CCS should              done as a research activity
          consider implementing     which involves three stages: 1)
          linkages and              Needs Analysis, 2)
          consortium among/with     Development and 3) Validation.
          other learning            Most of these are performed
          institutions for          and presented during the
          academic sharing of       college and campus research
          resources and             in-house review. In addition,
          available instructional   IMs are reviewed by a technical
          materials.                and review committee in the
                                    college, campus and university
     b. A more comprehensive        levels.
          review of faculty-made    Researches of faculty are given
          instructional materials   corresponding workload units
          and action researches     in addition to teaching load
          is suggested in view of   units of faculty members.
          producing universal       Overload units are given
          instructional materials   incentives in the form of service
          among subjects and in     credits which can be
          aid to the grant of       monetized.
          corresponding             A graduate tracer system is in
          incentives.               place to continually determine
                                    the relevance of BSCS
     c. The management may          curriculum by monitoring the
          consider the provision    employability of graduates.
          of research incentives
          (in any form) to faculty
          members undertaking
          instructional
          development and
          action researches.

     d. A continuing evaluation
          on the effectiveness
          and relevance of the
          BSCS curriculum is
          recommended using its
          statistically treated
          data to address
          technological
          development,
          employability of
          graduates and in
          pursuit of quality and
          excellence

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 45]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

RECOMMENDATIONS                   ACTION TAKEN                      PERCENTAGE
                                                                            OF REMARKS

                                                                    COMPLIANCE

2. Provision of internet service  CCS SBO provided two Wi-Fi        100%  On-going
    to the computer laboratories  routers with up to 1.5 MBPS       100%  On-going
    is recommended for            internet subscription each that
    students and faculty          are used by students for free     90%   On-going
    utilization in the            The college also has an annual    100%    Done
    reinforcement of activities   internet subscription of 5mbps    100%
    and research                  for faculty members and for             On-going
                                  computer laboratory room No.
3. Consider the specialization    7.The college also allotted a
    tracks under CMO No 34 s      reasonable budget for the
    2012 and CMO No 12 s          annual internet subscription for
    2013, respectively, in the    the rest of the computer
    periodic review and           laboratory rooms.
    enhancement of the
    curriculum.                   Straight and Ladderized
                                  curricular programs were
4. Conduct a periodic study, to   submitted to CHED for
    trace employability of        Certification of Contents
    graduates, analyze their      Notation, in compliance to the
    performance and feedbacks     minimum standards as
    of employers reflective of    prescribed in CMO 53 s 2006
    the program outcomes. A       and CMO 18 s 2008,
    faculty performance study is  respectively. The proposed
    also suggested.               curricular programs enrichment
                                  was “Contents Noted” by
5. Consider a laboratory          CHED Regional Office I. The
    assistant in the computer     said enrichment proposals are
    laboratory to assist the      now forwarded to the Board of
    students and faculty in       Regents for final approval and
    laboratory activities.        implementation.
                                  The College is also undergoing
6. Gradual purchase of            further curriculum enrichment
    appropriate licenses for      for BSCS Straight Curriculum
    software and computer         that will include Service
                                  Management Specialization
                                  Track on IT-BPO (Information
                                  Technology-Business Process
                                  Outsourcing) to meet the
                                  demands and needs of the
                                  steadily growing IT-BPO
                                  industry.

                                  A graduate tracer study is on-
                                  going utilizing an online
                                  Graduate Tracer System
                                  integrated in the campus
                                  website. The system enables
                                  alumni to fill out needed
                                  information. The system
                                  summarizes the collected data.
                                  The target completion date is
                                  December 2014.

                                  Two laboratory assistants were
                                  hired to assist faculty members
                                  and students in their laboratory
                                  activities. They ensure that
                                  before the start of every
                                  semester, the computer units
                                  are ready.

                                  Computer laboratory rooms are
                                  installed with open-source
                                  software. Gradual

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 46]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

RECOMMENDATIONS                    ACTION TAKEN                      PERCENTAGE
                                                                             OF REMARKS

                                                                     COMPLIANCE

    programs used in the           implementation is undertaken      100%    Done
    computer laboratories or the   so that students will not be      100%  On-going
    alternative use of “open-      overwhelmed by the sudden         100%
    source software” is advised.   change. Though licensed           100%    Done
                                   software will be maintained for         On-going
7. Syllabi used should be          courses that require one, open    75%
    regularly updated, signed      source is encouraged.             100%  On-going
    and duly approved by           Syllabi are updated, signed and         On-going
    concerned authorities.         approved by concerned
                                   authorities.
8. More teacher-made
    instructional materials, CAI,  Instructional materials were
    student guides, workbooks,     proposed and presented as
    operation manuals and          research. Continuous
    software prototypes may be     improvement is being done to
    developed.                     develop CAI, workbooks / work
                                   texts, operation manuals and
9. Repackaging OJT Manuals         software prototypes.
    and Capstone Project           OJT guidelines are a part of the
    Manual and have it             academic provisions in the
    approved by the appropriate    university faculty manual while
    authorities for adoption and   thesis guidelines are already
    implementation for the         approved for adoption and
    BSCS program.                  implementation.

10. Participation of the alumni,   Feedback from stakeholders
    students and                   and agencies where our
    representatives from the       students are deployed for their
    industry in the curriculum     On-the-Job Training were
    review, updates and            solicited to continually improve
    enhancement is                 the curriculum. Statistical data
    encouraged.                    from the graduate/alumni tracer
                                   study shall also serve as basis
11. More linkages with other       for curricular improvements.
    learning institutions for      The college is establishing
    exchange of developed          linkages with other learning
    instructional materials are    institutions.
    recommended.
                                   Gradual purchase of required
12. More collection of             references is being done.
    prescribed number of
    Computer Science books
    and references may be
    provided in the library.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 47]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                     EXTENSION

         Extension service is one of the quadric functions of the University. In fact,
it has become a criterion-component of accreditation. The University is not only
accredited on the basis of its excellence in teaching and research functions but
also of its service to the community.

         Extension services, as defined in the General Appropriations Act is an
inherent function of institution of higher learning with the purpose of initiating,
catalyzing, and sustaining the development of various communities, using their
experience and available resources. It is a vital component in creating a more
favorable, true to life teaching-learning experience for students and for the school
to bring to the community its expertise and resources.

         Extension services also involves packaging, demonstration, and
application of appropriate technology, tools, materials, processes and products,
generated through research and technical studies in selected communities for
countrywide adoption.

         It includes community organizing activities and similar extension, or
community development work.

         Extension is one of the three-fold functions of the state university that is
recognized and embodied in the Higher Education Modernization Act of 1997
(RA 8292) with regard to the intensification of the extension services together
with research and higher education that will be geared towards the provision of
better quality education and the development of middle and high level manpower.
The act also promotes the establishment of extension centers where
development shall be established at the communities, setting up the adoption of
modern and innovative modes of transmitting knowledge such as the use of
information technology, the dual system, open learning, community laboratory,
etc., for the promotion of greater access to higher education.

1. WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES

         The Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University through PD1778 is
    involved in the continuous generation of appropriate extension delivery
    systems in order for the people to attain the gains of development by
    alleviating the standard of living of the poor, creating employment, eliminating
    illiteracy, and providing access to social services and welfare.

         In line with this, as mandated in the University Code (2003), the Research
    and Extension functions of the University are carried to support instruction
    and production and in the context of the overall development plan of the
    University. The University Research and Extension Office (UREO) is tasked
    to develop a university-wide program that entails the conduct of community-
    extension related activities which involve all the academic department and
    units. It aims to verify and disseminate appropriate technologies and

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 48]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

    information which is in response to the priority needs of its various clienteles
    and contributes to the total development of communities in the province,
    region, and nation. This vision is directed towards the accomplishment of
    extension endeavors which are focused on relevant concerns in education,
    agriculture, agroforestry, fisheries, industry, health and nutrition, local
    government, trade, and socio-economic that is responsive to the immediate
    needs of clienteles.

         In 2002, the Professor-in-the-Barangay program was conceptualized as
    the university’s primary extension delivery system, creating a distinct identity
    for the university as a capable partner in achieving community development.
    This program aims to determine the socio-economic impact of the university
    in its service area. Specifically, the program shall:

             a. Develop extension delivery system;
             b. Establish a benchmark data on the socio-economic status of a

                  barangay;
             c. Prepare the barangay/clientele’s Integrated Development Plan;
             d. Strengthen linkages with GOs, NGOs and people’s organizations;

                  and
             e. Monitor and evaluate projects.

         The South La Union Campus (SLUC) upholds the university’s commitment
    to effectively implement its extension programs and community services. The
    Campus Extension Office, headed by a competent Extension Head, performs
    the major functions to guide every college in the identification, needs
    assessment, planning, coordination, implementation, monitoring and
    evaluation of extension activities of the different colleges/institutes. The goals
    of the campus extension office are anchored on the goals of the UREO. Part
    of the manifestation of its commitment to the development of the community
    is the implementation of framework of action that provides technical,
    educational, social, and health services to other agencies and communities.

         The extension projects and activities of the BS Computer Science
    program are anchored on the following specific objectives:

         a. To equip educators and other professionals with basic and advanced
             computer skills to be more productive and innovative in the teaching-
             learning process and in their respective professions.

         b. To share its Information and Communication Technology (ICT)
             resources in promoting computer literacy in its service areas.

         c. To help the community to alleviate their standard of living through
             outreach activities.

         d. To extend expertise to its linkages to enhance their operations with
             computer technologies.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 49]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

2. ADEQUATE AND RELEVANT PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES TO ACHIEVE
    OBJECTIVES
         The college is actively engaged in adequate and relevant
    projects/activities responsive to the needs, problems, and resources of the
    community in the field of Information and Communication Technology to
    achieve its extension objectives. These projects and activities include the
    following:
    1. To equip educators and other professionals with basic and advanced
         computer skills to be more productive and innovative in the teaching-
         learning process and in their respective professions.
         A. Computer Trainings. Along with the college’s curricular offering, it
             envisions to equip the educators and other professionals in the
             community with basic and advanced computer skills which they can
             use in their respective profession thus the conduct of the Computer
             Literacy Training Program (CLTP) and Advanced Computer Skills
             Development Training Program (ACSDTP) are done annually.
             a. Computer Literacy Training Program (CLTP) for Public
                  Elementary, Secondary and Tertiary School Teachers and
                  Other Professionals in La Union. This activity provides annual
                  training to elementary, secondary, tertiary public school teachers
                  and other professionals in La Union that started in 2002 for Phase I
                  and accomplished its Phase XI last March 2012.
                      These CLTP trainees were given training on MS Office
                  Applications (MS Word, MS Excel, and MS PowerPoint) and were
                  given a Pre-test for every beginning of a project and culminate with
                  a Post test. Teaching modules were issued to every participant
                  during the training period to enable them to move on or do practice
                  for mastery.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 50]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                      Figure 4 reflects the data on the number of clienteles served in
                  the last five years of the said training. Viewed in totality, it is
                  noteworthy to say that there are more participants in Phase XI
                  which implies that the CLTP training is in demand and more
                  computer literate public school teachers and other professionals in
                  La Union were produced (see Appendix J).

           25
            20
            15 Elementary
            10 High School

                                                                                                        LGU
             5
             0

                  Phase VII Phase Phase IX Phase X Phase XI
                      (34) VIII (30) (31) (29) (40)

               Figure 4. Distribution of Clienteles Served in the CLTP
             b. Advanced Computer Skills Development Training Program

                  (ACSDTP). Due to the flourishing result of CLTP and the
                  commitment to remain responsive and attuned to the needs of
                  teachers, the college conceived the Advanced Computer Skills
                  Training Program. This is intended for teachers who had finished
                  CLTP. This activity is composed of four projects namely: Project 1 –
                  Photo Editing Using Adobe Photoshop; Project 2- Desktop
                  Publishing Using MS Publisher; Project 3 – Creating Animation
                  Using Macromedia Flash MX; and Project 4 – Internet Access
                  Using Web Browsers.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 51]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

             It can also be seen in Figure 5 that most of the clienteles served
    are elementary teachers. On the other hand, secondary teachers are well
    represented. LGU employees also participated starting from Phase 1 and
    were completely trained in Phase 3 (see Appendix J).

25

20                                           Elementary Teachers
                                             High School Teachers
15                                           LGU Employees

10

 5

 0
        Phase I Phase II Phase III Phase IV
          (30) (32) (40) (35)

              Figure 5. Clienteles Served in the ACSDTP

    c. Computer Literacy Training Program for Educators in the 2nd
        District of La Union. Due to the sterling performance of the CLTP
        clients, the sponsors notably the Congressman of the 2nd District of
        La Union thought of expanding the program to the educators of the
        said district. It started last April 2011 for the Phase I and
        accomplished Phase IV last April 2013.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 52]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

            Based on Figure 6, the said training had served
   154educators from the different towns of the Second District of La
   Union which implies that more and more clienteles are being
   served by the college and transformed them to become more
   computer literate.

42                 Phase II  Phase III Phase IV
40
38
36
34
32
30

          Phase I

Figure 6. Number of Clients Served in the CLTP for Educators
                    in the Second District of La Union

2. To share its Information and Communication Technology (ICT) resources
    in promoting computer literacy in its service areas.
    B. Community Outreach. In order to achieve par excellence, a stabilized
         school-community partnership must be established. Hence, the
         College of Computer Science tied up with the Local Government Unit
         of Agooin order to promote computer literacy to its service area thus
         improving the computer skills of the community it serves. The College
         of Computer Science is actively engaged in different community
         outreach programs such as:
         a. Share-A-Ware Program for the Grade VI Pupils. The college also
             envisions helping young learners to become computer literate, thus,
             the college offered a Share-a-Ware program. This training is given
             to Grade VI elementary pupils on the basics of the computer and in
             using MS Office application. This program started in 2009 with
             Agoo East Elementary School as the cooperating school.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 53]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…
             b. Literacy Training Program for the Barangay. Aside from the

                  seminars given to the adopted barangay, the college also
                  conducted computer literacy training to the barangay officials,
                  OSYs, and interested residents. Participants are being trained on
                  the basics of computers as well as on the different office
                  applications.

    3. To help the community to alleviate their standard of living through
         outreach activities.
             c. Professor-in-the-Barangay. In order to alleviate the standard of
                  living of the community, the college also offered the Professor-in-
                  the-Barangay since 2002, which provides trainings and seminars to
                  the adopted barangay. The faculty, staff, and students share their
                  knowledge and skills by conducting trainings and seminars about
                  different topics given to the barangay officials, out-of-school youth
                  (OSY), and other interested residents.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 54]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

4. To extend expertise to its linkages to enhance their operations with
    computer technologies.
    a. Consultancy Services. In order to provide access to social services
       and welfare, the faculty members as well as the students share their
       technical expertise to partner agencies in enhancing their operations
       through system development. Faculty members of the college are
       tapped to develop systems which include the Agoo Unified ID
       System, Municipal Ordinance and Resolution Digital Archiving
       System, DMMMSU-SLUC Automated Enrolment System,
       Management Information System for Children (MISC) of the
       Municipality of Agoo, Management Information System for
       Employees (MISE) of the Municipality of Agoo, and the Municipal
       Ordinance Historical Tracking System.
             Moreover, there were systems developed by the students in
       their Thesis course, which were accepted by the clients. Some of
       these include: the Small Enterprise Technology Upgrading Project
       Web-based Project Monitoring System of Department of Science
       and Technology Regional Office I by Boado et al., the Computerized
       Tricycle Franchise Record System of the Municipality of Tubao by
       Galiste et al., and Online Record System of the Basilica of Our Lady
       of Charity, Agoo, La Union by Cachero et al.

4. SYSTEMATIC AND EFFECTIVE PROCEDURES

    The College of Computer Science is one of the pioneering institutions which
cater different extension programs to the community. It gears towards the
upliftment of the lives of the community it serves.

    In order to conduct the said extension activities, the college is guided with
systematic and effective procedures in line with the University Extension Manual.
The College Extension Office, with the leadership and supervision of the Dean
and the College Extension Facilitator, observes the procedures in planning,
implementation, monitoring and evaluation of every extension activity.

Planning  Implementation  Monitoring and
                             Evaluation

                                                       Feedback

                         Figure 8. The CCS Extension Activity Cycle
    The planning stage includes the identification of beneficiaries/client, needs
assessment, and development of training proposal and design. The extension
activities (CLTP, ACSDTP, Professor-in-the-Barangay, and Share-a-Ware) are
coordinated with the local government unit through the Chairman of the

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 55]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Committee of Education and Coordinator of the Municipal Literacy Council.
Request and acceptance of the services of the college were embodied in the
Memorandum of Agreement signed by both parties and other proper authorities.
Needs assessment activities such as focus groups, personal interviews, and
administration of survey questionnaires are conducted to identify priority needs of
the clientele which will be a major component to consider in the formulation and
development of training design. The college then proceeds to the preparation of
training materials such as modules, handouts, lecture notes and presentation
slides, laboratory resources and coordination with concerned party for the budget
allocation, venue preparation and other needed documents and information.

    The implementation is the actual conduct of the extension activity. During the
seminar/training proper, lectures and demonstrations are delivered clearly,
hands-on applications are carried out, copies of module, lecture notes, and other
training materials are provided, and multimedia presentations are used. This
stage includes the involvement of the participants, speakers/trainers, project
leaders, other faculty and staff, and students as facilitators.

    For computer literacy trainings (CLTP and ACSDTP), the training proper
takes 6 days (48 hours). The trainings are conducted in the computer laboratory
rooms in the College of Computer Science (CCS) from 8:00 AM to 5:00 PM. The
CCS teachers serve as trainers and facilitators. Teaching modules are issued to
every participant during the training period to enable them to move on or do
practice for mastery.

    For the Professor-in-the-Barangay, a computer literacy training is conducted
every third Wednesday of the month, 3:00-5:00 PM, using one of the Laboratory
Rooms of CCS as the venue. And every 4th Wednesday of the month, 3:00-5:00
PM, the scheduled trainers, student and faculty facilitators proceed to the
Barangay Hall to conduct seminars and other livelihood training activities.

    The computer laboratory rooms of the college are also being used for the
Share-a-Ware program for Grade VI pupils. The participants are trained on the
basics of the computer and in using MS Office application. The training is usually
conducted every Saturday from 8:00-11:00 AM. The faculty members serve as
trainers while the BSCS students serve as facilitators.

    The monitoring and evaluation of the extension activities provides a feedback
mechanism of the conducted extension activity. For the computer literacy
trainings, in order to determine the level of performance of the trainees, pretest
and posttest are conducted.

    Likewise, an evaluation questionnaire is administered to assess the
effectiveness of the extension activity. The participants also present their outputs
and on-the-spot impressions about their training, their trainers and facilitators and
venue which may serve as an evaluation of the training.

    In-house reviews and regular meetings are also conducted by the Campus
Extension Facilitator, the Director for Extension, and the Vice-President for

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 56]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Research and Extension where issues and updates concerning the conduct of
extension activities are discussed.

    In order to determine the effects of the training to the clienteles’ performance
of their work in their respective positions, an assessment of the CLTP was
conducted. The said study also identified the extent of utilization of the
knowledge and skills gained from the training. Moreover, to further sustain the
extension programs of the college, a study on the impact of the trainings
conducted is currently being undertaken.

    At present, the campus extension unit has designed the South La Union
Campus (SLUC) extension agenda, which will be a collaborative activity among
the different colleges/institutes. Figure 9 shows the framework for the formulation
of the extension agenda of the College of Computer Science. It is also on this
framework that the different extension programs and projects of the other
colleges of the campus were framed. These projects were based on the
mandates of DMMMSU, national and regional development thrusts, curricular
programs, current realities, and available technologies. More importantly, they
were also based on the needs and opportunities of the community/clientele.
Given these premises, the implementation or provision of these extension
programs and projects is expected to enhance or improve the knowledge, skills,
and attitudes of the target clientele. Consequently, the improvement or
enhancement of the knowledge, skills, and behavior or attitude of the clientele
will result to higher productivity, better performance efficiency, improved
management capability, better physical and social environment, and better health
condition. Finally, the empowerment of these communities and
institutions/organization will remarkably contribute to a better quality of life and
sustainable development (see Appendix K).

                           Figure 7. The College Extension Agenda

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 57]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

5. REASONABLE BUDGET

         The College Extension Programs are made viable through the
    appropriation of funds from the College Program of Expenditures, University
    Extension Budget, and Training Fees/Fund Support from Client or Partner
    Agency.

         As to the University Extension Budget, the Office of the University Budget
    Officer issues notice of cash allocations for extension every quarter. Special
    releases are made in case DBM provides additional funding. The University
    Research and Extension Office (UREO) prepare the quarterly budget release
    based on the amount released by the budget officer. The releases are made
    by campus, institute, or other units. The project/study leader shall have the
    authority to use the funds allocated for his/her study based on his/her
    operational plan. On the other hand, the accounting division controls the
    expenditures in accordance with the expense classes in the budget and sub-
    allotments.

         Budget Procedures based on University Extension Manual
         1. Release of approved budget for any study/project shall be based on

             the allocation indicated in the operational plan submitted to the campus
             and University Research and Extension Office. The release of funds
             from UREO shall be based on the request of the campus coordinators,
             recommended by the university extension coordinator and to be
             approved by the University Research and Extension director.
         2. Project leaders shall disburse according to accounting and auditing
             procedures. This shall be applied in all types of extension projects
             funded by local or foreign agencies.
         3. Supplies and materials contained in the operational plan shall be taken
             care of by the campus extension office under the responsibility of the
             coordinator, center/institute director.
         4. Extensionists shall conduct their extension projects on contract basis.
             Outputs shall be the basis of evaluating the performance of the
             extensionist, and shall determine whether she/he be allowed to
             conduct another extension project, i.e., after the submission of the
             terminal report/s.
         5. Collection of traveling expenses shall be subject to existing University
             and COA auditing, and accounting rules and regulations.
         6. Travels in connection with extension activities shall be based on
             guidelines/provisions on the delegation of authority as prescribed by
             the university and other existing rules and regulations.
         7. Proceeds from complete/ongoing extension (agency funded and
             special projects) shall be deposited and disbursed under the provisions
             of Fund 161, while funds from other government, non-government, and
             foreign-assisted (all special projects) shall be deposited and disbursed
             under the provisions of Fund 184.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 58]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

       8. Non-consumable supplies and materials purchased by the extensionist
           shall be submitted/turned-over to the campus/university upon the
           completion/termination of the project.

       Table 1. CCS Extension Budget Share from Campus Extension Fund

                         2011          2012                  2013

Travel                          6,569         5,300            6,750
Training                        1,000         3,500            3,000
Supplies                        8,100         8,002            8,150
Others                          6,798         9,400          11,725
Total                          22,467        26,202          29, 625

       Table 2. CCS Extension Share of Income from Fund 164

Areas of Budget                October – December    January – May
    Allocation                            2013              2014

Instructional Materials                24,764.30             37, 125.15
and Supplies

Travel                                 18,573.22             23, 203.22

Training/Seminars                      39,210.15             32, 484.51

Total                                  82,547.67             92, 812.88

    The budget allocation for extension services is equivalent to 10% of
TUITION FEES and will be used for instructional materials necessary for
effective technology transfer of research outputs to the community, skills
training in livelihood relative to the research outputs to the community, travel
expenses, training and seminar expenses of extension services personnel.
The allocation is fixed to ensure effective delivery of programs involving
technology transfer of research outputs.

    With the active extension services that the college caters, it has gained
trust from different sectors of the community and has invited external funding
resources to support its extension programs. Way back 2002, through proper
coordination of the former director of the Institute of Computer Science (now
the College of Computer Science), she tied up with the Municipality of Agoo
and Agoo Local School Board in order to support the extension programs of
the college.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 59]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

6. PROVISION OF MATERIALS AND OTHER RESOURCES

         As to the provision of materials and other resources, the college is
    equipped with faculty, staff, and students who are knowledgeable in the field
    of Information Technology and other related fields to serve as trainers,
    resource speakers and facilitators.

         The college is also equipped with the state-of-the-art computer laboratory
    facilities and packaged technologies which can be utilized during trainings.
    The college follows specific guidelines such as the following:

    a. The Institute for Research and Local Administration (IRLA) serves as the
         training center of the University; hence, activities conducted using the
         facilities should enter into a contract or a memorandum of agreement. This
         is to be coordinated by the Continuing Education Coordinator and
         recommended for approval by the URE Director and finally approved by
         the President.

    b. Borrowers/users of University Extension property are required to do the
         following:
             a. Get clearance from the person in-charge;
             b. Seek permission and approval from the director;
             c. Should not move the property from one place to another to prevent
                  damage as well as loss; and
             d. Be responsible and accountable for any loss, destruction, and
                  vandalism on the property.

    c. The use of DMMMSU facilities and equipment may be availed of by the
         clientele provided that there is a written request and approval of the URE
         director using DMMMSU R and E Form No. 17 or through the use of
         contract or memorandum of agreement.

    d. All existing equipment and facilities purchased from the funds of local and
         foreign-assisted projects shall become the property of the University.

         In addition, the appropriation of funds from the College Program of
    Expenditures, University Extension Budget, and Training Fees/Fund Support
    from the Client or Partner Agency to finance all supplies and materials used in
    the preparation of pertinent documents, coordination with client agencies and
    the conduct and monitoring of extension activities.

7. PARTICIPATION OF SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF FACULTY/ STAFF/
    STUDENTS/ COMMUNITY IN MAJOR PROJECTS/ ACTIVITIES

         The success of any undertaking lies on how the different parties interact
    and participate with one another. Thus, the success of the extension
    programs of the college would not have been possible without the valiant
    figures who contributed their expertise, time and effort. The administration
    spearheads the extension programs as consultant and project
    leader/organizer in every extension program. Meanwhile, faculty members of
    the college were tapped to train the teachers, other professionals and

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 60]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

community members and serve as facilitators during trainings (see Appendix
G, H, and I).

    The figure below shows the percentage of participation of CCS faculty
members in the different extension programs of the college from 2010-2014.

Percentage  100 93.75 100 96.875 93.75 100      Computer Trainings (CLTP,
             90                                 ACSDTP)
             80 72
             70 63                              Community Outreach (PIB,
             60 50 50                           Share-a-Ware)
             50 44
             40
             30
             20
             10
               0
                      2010 2011 2012 2013 2014

Figure 8. Percentage of Faculty Members Who Participated in the
                         Different Extension Activities

    The students also served as facilitators in the Professor-in-the-Barangay,
CLTP for the Barangay and Share-a-Ware Program. Furthermore, the
stakeholders served as consultants, project coordinators, sponsors, and
trainees.

8. AWARDS OF DISTINCTION AND ACHIEVEMENT AND GRANTS OF THE
    PROGRAM, “BEST PRACTICES” ADOPTED

    One of the greatest achievements of the Extension program of the college
is its contribution to the Municipality of Agoo in winning the much-coveted
2009 UNESCO Confucius Prize for Literacy Award.

    The college extension program also received a certificate of recognition as
a recipient of a Municipal Resolution of Recognition during the Pammadayaw
Ti Umili for its invaluable support to the CLTP for Educators in Public
Elementary and Secondary Schools and to the Municipal Employees of Agoo
on May 3, 2012.

    In addition, the college extension facilitator bagged “SLUC Campus
Extension Worker of the Year” during the University Foundation Day-Campus
Celebration last January 2014 for exemplary performance in making
extension projects sustainable

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 61]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         .

         The CCS faculty members during the awarding ceremonies in which the
extension activities of the college were recognized. Furthermore, Lucille N.
Dacaymat (upper right) was awarded extension worker for the year 2013.

         Dr. Agustin Veras, former dean of the College of Computer Science,
    receives the recognition for its computer literacy programs from LGU-Agoo
    headed by Hon. Sandra Eriguel during the Pamadayaw ti Umili.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 62]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Extent of Compliance with the Teams’ Recommendations for Area VI
(Extension) in the last survey:

Recommendations                  Actions Taken           Percentage of    Remarks
                                                          Compliance      Continuing
1. Strengthen linkages/tie-       MOAs were
     ups with the local             notarized                 100%          activity
     government and other                                     100%        Continuing
     agencies by having           Created MOA and
     MOAs/MOUs notarized            MOU                       100%          activity

                                  Notarized MOA              100%      Accomplished
                                    and MOU
                                                                           On-going
2. Develop an instrument          Accomplishment
      or scheme for each            reports were
      project to reflect the        based on the
      plan and the actual           monitoring &
      accomplishment for            evaluation forms
      them to consider re-          for research &
      planning if their targets     extension projects
      are not attained.             to reflect the plan
                                    and actual
                                    accomplishment

                                  Re-planning was
                                    conducted for
                                    objectives which
                                    were not attained

3. Conduct assessment of          Conducted an
     all extension projects to      impact
     evaluate the                   assessment of
     effect/impact of such          the computer
     for the college to be          trainings (CLTP
     able to know what to           and ACSDTP)
     consider if objectives
     are not attained.

4. Submit to potential            Presented the
     funding agencies               impact
     (private or other              assessment to
     national government            the Department of
     agencies) the                  Education
     packaged impact                (DepEd) – La
     assessment of the              Union for
     projects to further the        potential funding
     cause of the program
     and to further support       Planned to submit
     sustainability of              impact
     extension projects.            assessment
                                    package to other
                                    agencies such as

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 63]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Recommendations               Actions Taken           Percentage of  Remarks
                                                       Compliance

                              CHED.

5. If budget warrants,         Since there are       100%            No available
     consider the                no appropriations                      budget for
     construction of an          yet for the                         construction of
     improved extension          construction of a
     office with adequate        new college                              a new
     facilities for              extension office,                      extension
     extensionist/faculty to     the college
     attend walk-in clients      transferred its                           office
     and which is conducive      extension office to
     for extension functions     a more conducive
     e.g. meetings,              and accessible
     consultations, etc.         location to be
                                 able to attend to
                                 walk-in clients
                                 and other
                                 extension
                                 functions

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 64]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                                      RESEARCH

1. WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES

    a. University
                  The College of Computer Science supports the University in

         promoting research. It engages its faculty and students in research-related
         activities. DMMMSU’s research vision and mission is “to be globally
         competitive as a University of distinctive excellence in science and
         technology guided by the research agenda of the line agencies of the
         country to achieve a peaceful, equitable, self-sufficient, and ecologically
         balanced society.”

                  The goal of the University Research Unit is to generate and verify
         appropriate technologies and information in response to the priority needs
         of its various clienteles.

                  As such, the research programs of the University include the areas
         of Education and Information and Communication Technology (ICT),
         which focus on instructional materials development, teaching
         competencies and effectiveness, application of ICT in teaching and
         learning, policy, web interfaces, and information systems, among others.

                  DMMMSU research activities are linked to the country’s vision to
         strengthen agricultural and education and to grow confidently into industry
         and services to achieve a peaceful, equitable, self-sufficient, and
         ecologically-balanced society.

                  This year, there are seven (7) research objectives that are
         formulated, to wit: (1) to generate technologies that are relevant to the
         needs of Region 1, disseminate research outputs through presentations to
         scientific fora, publication to refereed journals and application for patents,
         (2) to mentor budding researchers resulting to increased percentage of
         faculty members conducting research and generating more relevant
         research outputs to address the needs of the region, (3) to empower
         researchers to be globally competitive in the generation of technologies
         through capability building , (4) to upgrade/establish laboratory facilities
         and equipment for the conduct of basic, applied, and action researches,
         (5) to sustain and further establish linkages with local and international
         funding agencies (6) to apply for CHED Accredited Research Journal, and
         (7) to sustain the two national centers (SRDI and NARTDI), one regional
         center (PCC), and to evaluate the performance of existing research and
         development centers of the University.

                  The University research plans jibe with the national research
         agenda of funding agencies and the regional research agenda.

    b. College of Computer Science
                  The College of Computer Science maintains its commitment to

         engage and motivate faculty and students in research undertakings. The
         College’s research objectives are:

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 65]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         i. To enhance research culture through active participation in the conduct
             of research and participation in trainings, workshops, and conferences

         ii. To establish good affiliations to different organizations through
             memberships and involvement in various research endeavors that
             heightens capability of the researchers.

         iii. To inculcate the value of research in academic growth and
             development through utilization and dissemination of conducted
             researches

         iv. To orient the researchers of the policies and procedures of the
             University and provide full support and constant monitoring of their
             researches and involvement in research undertakings.

                  Moreover, the College focuses on researches parallel to the
         Department of Science and Technology (DOST) research objectives, the
         University research agenda, and the National Higher Education Research
         Agenda, as follows:
         i. Studies on the development, implementation and assessment (DOST)

             of models and materials including instructional materials, processes,
             learning and procedure, and policies (NHERA 2, Agendum 3)
         ii. Software development (NHERA 2 agendum 3, DOST) and usability
             testing (NHERA 2 agendum 4) of implemented software in learning
             and organizational procedure/ operations
         iii. Impact study (institution)
         iv. Graduate tracer and student services(DOST, institution)
             (see Appendix O)

2. ADEQUATE AND RELEVANT PROJECTS/ ACTIVITIES TO ACHIEVE
         OBJECTIVES

         Faculty and students conduct relevant projects and activities to achieve
the College’s objectives. They conduct researches, participate to seminars,
conferences, and other research activities.

    1. Enhance research culture through active involvement in the conduct of
         research and participation in trainings, workshops, and conferences

                  The College participates in capability-building activities
         (seminars/ trainings, paper presentations). The College conducts and
         attends different capability-building activities. It actively participates in
         conferences, trainings/ workshops, and seminars. Faculty members have
         presented their research papers to international audience, and have
         attended workshops and national convention for IT educators. This year
         (as of November), there were four (4) international conferences which
         were attended by the faculty members, namely: 7th IEEE Conference on
         HNICEM, 2ndInternational Conference on e-Learning and e-Educational
         Technologies, International Youth and Educators Summit on
         Transformative Education, and South East Asian Conference on Graft and

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 66]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Corruption and Institutional Research, and International Conference on
         eLearning and Knowledge Management Technologies; and various
         trainings and workshops such as Book Writing Workshop, and Use of
         Statistical Software. In 2013, there were three (3) international, and three
         (3) national and institutional capability-building activities where faculty
         members presented their researches, and were trained and involved in
         planning. These were the: World Research Festival 2013, 3rdInternational
         Conference on E-Learning and Knowledge Management Technologies, 3rd
         International Conference on Multidisciplinary Research, Innovative ICT
         Development, National Engineering and Science Research
         Conference,11th National e-Learning Conference, and the Research and
         Extension Planning cum Workshop. In 2011-2012, there were five
         (5)papers presented in national and international conferences. These
         conferences include: 11th National e-Learning Conference in Dumaguete
         City, National Engineering and Science Research Conference in Pasay
         City, 3rd International Conference on Multidisciplinary Research in Bacolod
         City, Negros Oriental, 2011 International Educational Technology
         Conference, in KMUT Bangkok, Thailand, and 1st International Conference
         on Using IT in Education, Chulalongkorn University, Thailand (see also
         Appendix Q).

                  In 2012, there were ten (10) capability-building activities attended
         by CCS which were directly and indirectly related to the conduct of
         research (see Appendix X).

`

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 67]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         The College produces students and faculty researches. Students’
researches have been mostly on software development, and social and
experimental researches where the researches are examined through a proposal
and final defense. While, as of this year 2014, faculty researchers are doing the
assessment of current practices and needs and development of systems and
instructional materials. Among the researches that are related to the production
and use of instructional materials are:

                  Burgos, F.S. and Munar, E. A.(2013). Worktext in Automata and
                  Language Theory: A Needs Assessment. Faculty Journal
                  Volume 1 No. 1 College of Computer Science, DMMMSU-
                  SLUC.

                  Burgos, F.S. and Munar, E.A. Worktext in Automata and
                  Language Theory with Java for Formal Language and Automata
                  Package (JFLAP) (ongoing)

                  Dacanay, K.T.and Dacanay, E.G. (2013). Worktext in Discrete
                  Structures: Needs Analysis. Faculty Journal Volume 1 No. 1
                  College of Computer Science, DMMMSU-SLUC.

                  Dacanay, K.T. and Dacanay, E.G.Worktext in Professional
                  Ethics in Information Technology: Needs Analysis.

                  Dacaymat, L.N., Balcita, MC.G., Milan, JA.M. Development of
                  the Module in Computer Programming 1 (on-going)

                  Dacaymat, L.N.,Balcita, MC.G.and Milan, JA.M (2013). Module
                  in Computer Programming I: Needs Assessment

                  Duran, I. L. Needs Assessment in the Development of a Book
                  “Computer Concepts and Fundamentals” (on-going)

                  Limson, H. Module for Web Programming: Needs Analysis (on-
                  going)

                  Marzan, C.S. Albarillo, C.V., Baculo, MJ.C.,De Vera,
                  NR.G.,Dungan, B.M. and Munar, E.A. Module in Network
                  Principles and Programming: Needs Analysis (on-going).

                  Soria, A.V., Boado, R. and Mendoza, F.H. (2013) Worktext in
                  Operating System: Needs Analysis

                  Researches conducted also contribute to the empowerment of
         the students directly or indirectly, before and after they graduate. These
         researches are:

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 68]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  Cabanban, CL.G.(2014). e-Cloud: Online Collaborative Learning
                  Tools in Education. International Journal of Information
                  Technology and Computer Science (IJITCS)Volume 16 Issue
                  2.ISSN 2091-1610

                  Cabanban, CL.G. (2014). User Perception and Acceptance of
                  Mobile Learning in Higher Education. (Presented during the
                  Asian Network of Youth Volunteers, Philippine Normal
                  University Intl Youth and Educators Summit on Transformative
                  Education, Boracay, Philippines)

                  Cabanban, C.L.G. (2013). Development of Mobile Learning
                  Using Android Platform (Phase 1). International Journal of
                  Information Technology and Computer Science Volume 9 Issue
                  1. ISSN online: 2091-1610. (Presented during the 3rd
                  International Conference on E-Learning and Knowledge
                  Management Technologies, Rembrandt Hotel, Sukhumvit Soi
                  18, Sukhumvit Road, Bangkok, Thailand April 6-7, 2013)

                  Duran, I.L., Dacanay, M. G., De Vera, NR. G.(2013). Class
                  Schedule: A Predictor of Student’s Performance in Computer
                  Subjects. (Presented during the International Youth and
                  Educators Summit on Transformative Education, Boracay.
                  Feb7-10, 2014)

                  Duran, I.L. Llavore, D.C., Dungan, B. M. (2013).Study Habits
                  and the Performance of the BSCS Students in Computer
                  Programming 1. (Presented during the Intl Youth and Educators
                  Summit on Transformative Education, Boracay,
                  Philippines.Feb7-10, 2014)

                  Duran, I.L. (2013). K-12 Online Grading System.International
                  Association for Multidisciplinary Research Journal Vol. 7
                  October 2013 Print ISSN: 2243-8327 Online ISSN 2244-0429.
                  (Presented during the World Research Festival 2013, Marco
                  Polo Hotel, Davao City. May 1-4, 2013)

                  Duran, I.L. (2012).Relative Effectiveness of Virtual Laboratory
                  Strategies in Teaching Physics. (Presented during the World
                  Research Festival 2013, Marco Polo Hotel, Davao City, May 1-
                  4, 2013)

                  Duran, I.L. (2011). Meta-Analysis on the Role of Mathematics
                  Background in the Performance of BSCS Freshmen in
                  Computer Programming Subjects. (Presented during the 3rd
                  International Conference on Multidisciplinary Research, Planta

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 69]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  Centro Hotel and Residences, Bacolod City, Negros Oriental,
                  Philippines, February 7-9, 2013)

                  Duran, I.L. Academic Accomplishment: A Key Factor of
                  Teacher’s Performance by Isidro L. Duran (on-going)

                  Estacio, S.L., Marzan, C. S., Munar, E.A., Dungan, B.M.,
                  Baculo, MJ. C.(2014).Student Services in the College of
                  Computer Science DMMMSU.

                  Marzan, C.S. (2012). iLearn: A Courseware for Professional
                  Courses of the College of Computer Science, DMMMSU-SLUC.
                  (Presented during the 2013 National Engineering and Science
                  Research Conference, Heritage Hotel, Roxas Blvd. Pasay City
                  March 7, 2013 and during the 11th National Elearning
                  Conference, Bethel Guest House & Siliman University,
                  Dumaguete City. December 7-8, 2012)

                  Panay F.Q. (2011).A Self-Paced Instruction through Mobile
                  Technology in Heterogeneous Settings. DMMMSU-SLUC CE
                  Faculty Journal Vol 13. No. 1 ISSN 0119-4046

                  Panay F.Q.(2011). Conceptual Design of Technical
                  Infrastructure for e-Learning Delivery System on a Multi-
                  Campus Environment. DMMMSU-SLUC CE Research Journal
                  Vol 13. No. 1 ISSN 0119-4046

                  Panay F.Q.(2011). A Study on How Contents can be distributed
                  through a Multi-Channel Service. DMMMSU-SLUC CE
                  Research Journal Vol 15. No. 1 ISSN 0119-4046

                  Panay F.Q.(2011).The Didactical Use of Mobile Technologies to
                  Bridge Formal and Informal Learning. DMMMSU-SLUC CE
                  Research Journal Vol 13. No. 2 ISSN 0119-4046

                  Panay F.Q. (2011).Philippines towards Enhancing Information
                  and Communications Technology Competitiveness. Journal of
                  Information and Communication Technology in Education
                  (JICTE) Special Issue. King Mongkut’s University of Technology
                  North Bangkok, Bangsue, Bangkok. And in DMMMSU-SLUC
                  CE Faculty Journal Vol 14. No. 1 ISSN 0119-4046(Presented in
                  the 1st International Conference on Using IT in Education,
                  Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand).

                  Panay F.Q. (2011). Utilizing mLearning in Strengthening Logical
                  and Analytical Skills as a Foundation in Information and
                  Communications Technology Course.DMMMSU-SLUC CE
                  Research Journal Vol 15. No. 1 ISSN 0119-4046

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 70]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  Panay F.Q. (2011). Strengthening the Information Technology
                  Programs through Web 2.0 Technology in a Selected Higher
                  Learning.DMMMSU-SLUC CE Research Journal Vol 13. No. 1
                  ISSN 0119-4046

                  Panay F.Q. (2011).Future Trend of Education – Mobile Learning
                  Problems and Prospects. Journal of Information and
                  Communication Technology in Education (JICTE) Special Issue.
                  King Mongkut’s University of Technology North Bangkok,
                  Bangsue, Bangkok and DMMMSU-SLUC CE Research Journal
                  Vol 14. No. 2 ISSN 0119-4046. (Presented in the 2011
                  International Educational Technology Conference).

                  Suguitan, A. S., Dacanay, E. G., Marzan, C.S. Dacanay, K. T.
                  Graduate Tracer Study of DMMMSU-SLUC College of
                  Computer Science by (on-going)

                  Veras, Jr., A.R. (2013).Proposed Blended Learning Program for
                  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University South La Union
                  Campus (DMMMSU-SLUC). (Presented during the Research
                  Festival 2013, Marco Polo Hotel, Davao City, May 1-4, 2013)

                  Veras, Jr., A. R. and Munar, E. A.(2014).An Analysis on Class
                  Disruptions in the College of Computer Science, DMMMSU
                  SLUC.

     2. Establish good affiliations to different organizations through memberships
         and involvement in various research endeavors that heighten capability of
         the researchers.

                   Memberships/ affiliations. To strengthen its research, the college
         establishes affiliations with different organizations in the local/ national/
         international levels for assistance. In return, these organizations are
         provided with technical assistance by the students and the faculty. A
         memorandum of agreement is signed by the two parties. Students provide
         this technical assistance through their On-the-Job Training, and projects
         they develop. There are also research organizations in which the faculty
         are members and/or has participated or contributed in its different
         activities. Some of these organizations include the International
         Association of Multidisciplinary Research (IAMURE), Philippine
         Association of Institutions Research(PAIR), Asian Educational Research
         Association (AERA), Philippine E-learning Society (PELS), Electronic-
         International Scientific Research Journal Consortium (E-ISRJC),
         Computing Society of the Philippines (CSP), Philippine Society of
         Information Technology Educators (PSITE), Philippine National e-Learning

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 71]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Association, Philippine Web Accessibility Group, Philippine Learning
         Society, Internet Society and Ubuntu Community (see also Appendix U).

    3. Inculcate the value of research in academic growth and development
         through utilization and dissemination of conducted researches

                  Utilization/ Implementation of research outputs. Utilization of
         research outputs is also the concern of the College. Researches entitled
         “Awareness and Acceptability of the Community on the Ladderized
         Education Program” and “Assessment of Manpower Needs of the
         Industries, Private and Public Agencies in La Union” in 2007 contributed to
         the offering of the Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Ladderized
         Education Program (BSCS-LEP) which is still offered in the College.

                  There were also researches that were conducted which contributed
         to the improvement of instructional processes, like the “Relative
         Effectiveness of Modules in the Advanced Computer Skills Development
         Training Program” and “Relative Effectiveness of Modules in the
         Computer Literacy Training Program.” The Modules were used in the
         conduct of the extension program of the College.

                  A research for extension services entitled “Needs, Problems, and
         Resources Assessment of Barangay San Nicolas East: Basis for
         Extension Activities” was also conducted. It involved community survey to
         find out the available resources, existing conditions, the priority and needs
         of the community. Currently, San Nicolas East is served by the Professor-
         in-the-Barangay (PIB) Program.

                  In addition, there were systems developed by the students in their
         Thesis course, which were accepted by the clients. Some of these studies
         include: the Small Enterprise Technology Upgrading Project, Web-based
         Project Monitoring System of Department of Science and Technology
         Regional Office I by Boado et al., and Online Record System of the
         Basilica of Our Lady of Charity, Agoo, La Union by Cachero et al.

                  Other researches concerning the community, environment
         and/ or conservation of resources are :(see Appendix P).

                  Casem, E.E.and Cabanban, CL.G.Computer-Based Test (CBT)
                  System for Higher Education Institutions

                  Dacaymat, L.N. (2013).Needs, Problems, and Resources
                  Assessment of Barangay San Nicolas East: A Basis for
                  Extension Activities.CCS Research and Extension Journal
                  ISSN: 1656-1287 Volume 9 (1) (April-September 2013)

                  Duran, I.L. Waste Management Practices of the Coastline Areas
                  of the Municipality of Agoo (on-going)

                  Milan, JA. M. (2013). Impact of the Computer Literacy Training
                  Program and Advanced Computer Skills Development Training

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 72]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

                  Form 124 Trainees (article).CCS Research and Extension
                  Journal ISSN: 1656-1287 Volume 9 (1) (April-September 2013)

                  Munar, E.A. (2011).Computer Knowledge and Skills of
                  Barangay Councils in Pangasinan: A Survey.Journal of
                  Business, Education, Science and Technology, Vol 1 Issue 1

                  Panay, F.Q.(2011). ePUB files for Mobile Devices and eReader.
                  Journal of Information and Communication Technology in
                  Education (JICTE) Special Issue. King Mongkut’s University of
                  Technology North Bangkok, Bangsue, Bangkok. And
                  DMMMSU-SLUC CE Research Journal Vol 13. No. 2 ISSN
                  0119-4046. (Presented at the 2011 International Educational
                  Technology Conference, Bangkok, Thailand)

                  Veras Jr. A.R.,Songcuan, J.P., Abad, E.G. and Meneses, F.R.
                  (2013).Usability of the Agoo Unified ID System. (Presented
                  during the South East Asian Conference on Graft and
                  Corruption and Institutional Research. Jan 30-31, 2014)

                  Veras, Jr., A.R., Songcuan, J.P., Villanueva, C.P., Estilong, J.L.
                  (2013). Usability of the Municipal Ordinance and Resolution
                  Digital Archiving System. (Presented during the South East
                  Asian Conference on Graft and Corruption and Institutional
                  Research. Jan 30-31, 2014)

                  Veras Jr. A.R., Songcuan, J.P., Abad, E. and Villanueva, C.A.
                  (2014). Usability of Management Information System for
                  Children (MISC) of the Municipality of Agoo

                  Veras Jr., A.R., Songcuan, J.P., Abad, E. and Villanueva, C.A.
                  (2014). Usability of Management Information System for
                  Employees (MISE) of the Municipality of Agoo

                  Veras Jr., A.R., Songcuan, J.P., Abad, E. and Villanueva, C.A.
                  (2014). Usability of Municipal Ordinance Historical Tracking
                  System.

             In addition, the College encourages publication of researches. The
    College publishes a Research and Extension Journal. To date, eight (8)
    volumes (with two issues per volume) were already released by the College.
    They contain student research abstracts (in the earlier volumes), research-
    based articles, research, and extension papers of its faculty and students.
    The Journal is registered under the National Library with an ISSN 1656-1287.
    The first volume was released in 2004 while Volume 7 of the journal was
    published online through the e-International Scientific Research Journal
    Consortium.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 73]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

             This shows that the College supports publication and copyright of
    researches. There are researches which are included in journals, books of
    abstracts/ proceedings of different international conferences, published
    electronically, and copyrighted. Among the researches in an electronic
    journal include: “e-Cloud Collaborative Learning Tools in Education”
    (International Journal of Information Technology and Computer Science
    (IJITCS) ISSN 2091-1610 Volume 16 Issue 2), “Digital Library for the
    Graduate School of DMMMSU-SLUC, Agoo, La Union” (E-ISRJ ISSN 2094-
    1749, Volume 2 Issue 3), “e-Learning for Computer Programming 2 for
    DMMMSU Institute of Computer Science” (E-ISRJ ISSN 2094-1749, Volume
    2 Issue 2), “Job Portal for Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University”
    (E-ISRJ ISSN 2094-1749, Volume 2 Issue 3), and “Development of Mobile
    Learning Using Android Platform” (International Journal of Information
    Technology and Computer Science ISSN 2091-1610). From 2011 to
    November 2014, twenty (20) of the faculty researches were presented in
    national (3) and international conferences (12). Twenty-five(25) researches
    were published in international and institutional journals and books of
    abstracts/ proceedings (see Appendix Q).

4. Orient the researchers of the policies and procedures of the University and
    provide full support and constant monitoring of their researches and
    involvement in research undertakings.

                  The College follows a systematic procedure implemented by the
    University from research proposal presentation, approval, conduct, monitoring
    and completion of the research. Likewise, students conduct researches and
    are guided by the activities in their Thesis course (please see 3. Systematic
    and Effective Procedure). Moreover, budget (please see 4. Reasonable
    Budget) and materials and resources (please see 5. Provision of Materials
    and Other Resources) are available to support the faculty members of their
    research endeavors.

3. SYSTEMATIC AND EFFECTIVE PROCEDURES

         The College adheres to the procedures implemented by the University
from proposal presentation up to the submission of the terminal reports, and the
monitoring of the research activities. These are rigidly observed to generate
smooth implementation of any research activity. Guidelines and procedures are
discussed in the DMMMSU Research Manual.

         Documents needed in the research are prepared. Individual researchers
submit their operational plan (OPLAN) in which targets are stated. These
OPLANS are reviewed by the Research Head and recommended for approval by
the Chancellor. Further review is done by the Director of Research and
recommended for approval by the Vice President for Research and Extension
before endorsing them to the Office of the President for final approval.

         The faculty researchers also prepare an accomplishment report to monitor
the progress of on-going researches by a Monitoring Team. The research

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 74]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

facilitator prepares a quarterly report which is submitted to the Campus Research
Officeto monitor the performance of the College in research. The facilitator also
prepares Work and Financial Plan (WFP). This plan includes both the on-going
and new researches identified for inclusion in the budget. Preferences of projects
to be included in the WFP are the following:

         a. On-going projects recommended for continuation during the Agency In-
             House Review (AIHR)

         b. Proposals finally approved during the AIHR with OPLAN approved by
             concerned personnel

         An Agency In-House Review (AIHR) is conducted to evaluate researches-
proposed, on-going, or completed. The faculty members participate in these in-
house reviews for the evaluation of their research. The evaluation resultsare
forwarded to the respective researcher for their guidance.

         As for student researches, the College forms an Oral Examination
Committee (OrEC) that will evaluate the research proposals and completed
researches through a proposal and final defense. This is done during their Thesis
(1 and 2) courses. These researches are conducted in one school year in partial
fulfillment of their requirements for their degree. Thesis 1 allows students to
prepare and present their thesis proposal while Thesis 2 involves data gathering,
analysis and presentation of their completed research. The students are to
design and program a system or software that will facilitate a certain operation
making use of new technology; contribute to the solutions of existing and future
problems of our society especially in the area of information and communication
technology; and shall defend the developed and designed system. Specifically,
the course includes the following:

    a. Formulating the research problem
    b. Preparing and writing the preliminaries
    c. Preparing and writing Chapter 1 – Introduction
    d. Preparing and writing Chapter 2 – Methodology
    e. Oral Examination of the Thesis Proposal
    f. Revision and submission of the Thesis Proposal
    g. Development, data gathering, and analysis
    h. Preparing and writing Chapter 3 – Results and Discussion
    I. Preparing and writing Chapter 4 – Summary, Conclusions and

         Recommendations
    J. Preparing and writing other parts of the thesis (literature cited,

         appendices, cover page, etc.)
    k. Final oral examination of the Thesis
    l. Revision and submission of the Thesis

4. REASONABLE BUDGET

         In the aforementioned activities, assistance is provided. There is a
monthly budget release for the campus in a year. The budget is based on the
allocation indicated in the operational plan.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 75]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         Faculty members who undergo trainings or attend conferences, seminar
workshops or paper presentations and other related activities may also request
for support. Travel Order is accomplished. Budget can be requested by the
concerned faculty members and shall be endorsed and reviewed for approval.
Travels shall be based on guidelines/ provisions of the funding agency and on
the delegation of authority as prescribed by the university and other existing rules
and regulations. The collection of travelling expenses is subject to existing
University and COA auditing and accounting rules and regulations.

         Budget is also appropriated for the different research projects / activities of
the College such as the production of the Research and Extension Journal,
attendance to trainings and seminars, and institutional memberships for the
college (see Appendix L,M,N).

5. PROVISION OF MATERIALS AND OTHER RESOURCES

         Availability of Research Framework. Research and development
framework is carefully established to support these research endeavors. Policies
and guidelines are reviewed to support researchers in their activities; personnel
are designated and other support services are provided for research-related
needs.

         The Campus Research Office is headed by the Head and the University
Research Office is headed by a Director who report to the Vice President for
Research and Extension. It is the service unit that assists the College faculty,
staff, and students in their research undertakings. The Office, together with its
research facilitators from each college, provides assistance in processing
proposals and requests and in coordinating and stimulating research activities.

         Availability of facilities, equipment, and other resources. The
computer laboratory rooms may be used by the faculty members in their
research activities. There is also a Defense Room for student’s theses and
faculty members’ research and presentations, and a Mini Library/ Student Center
where students can stay for research and other student-related activities.

         Provision of supplies and materials. Supplies and materials contained
in the operational plan are under the custody of the Campus Research Office.
The Research facilitator receives supplies and materials from said Office and
distributes the supplies to the faculty researchers or released them as per their
request.

6. PARTICIPATION OF SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF FACULTY/ STUDENTS/
    COMMUNITY IN MAJOR PROJECTS/ ACTIVITIES

         Participation of faculty in the conduct of research. As of November of
this year, there were seventeen (17) faculty members who were sent to
conferences, seminars, and trainings/ workshops related to research. Seven (7)
of them presented their research papers to international audience and sixteen
(16)were sent to a workshop on book writing, participated in the agency-in-house

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 76]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

reviews and seminar on the use of statistical software. As of September 2014,
there were eleven (11) researches that were completed, and eleven (11) on-
going researches. In 2013, twenty-two (22) of the faculty members completed
fourteen (14) researches, six (6) faculty members presented papers in research
conferences, and some were trained and were involved in planning. In the past
year, almost all of the faculty members participated in the conduct of research
where they involve the community as the beneficiary. Presently, they are
conducting studies and are involved in institutionalized researches such as the
graduate tracer and student services.

With on-going/ completed research            94%

Publications (International, National,       72%
                         Local)

Research Presentations (International,  38%
             National and Regional)

                                               0% 50% 100%

Figure 11. Faculty Participation in Research (2011-2014)

                  Figure 11 summarizes the involvement of the faculty members in
         publications, presentations, and conduct of research. Thirty(30) have on-
         going and completed researches, twenty-three(23) have publications in
         the international, national, and local levels, while twelve (12) have
         presented in the international and national research conferences (see also
         Appendix P and Q).

         Participation of students in the conduct of research. Figure 12
summarizes the number of student researches from 2011 to 2014.

32                                                       67  2014
        44                                   57              2013
                                                             2012
                                                             2011

               Figure 12. Number of Student Researches (2011-2014)

         From 2011 to 2013, there were one hundred sixty-eighth (168) completed
student researches, with forty-four (44) in 2011, fifty-seven (57) in 2012, sixty-
seven (67) in 2013; and thirty-two (32) in 2014. All of the graduating students are
required to complete the Thesis course that requires a research study.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 77]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

7. AWARDS, INCENTIVES AND RECOGNITIONS

         Awards, incentives, and recognitions are given by the University for
meritorious and outstanding achievements in the field of research. They are
attributed to deserving faculty researchers. Certificate and/or monetary incentive
is awarded for a research output published in refereed journal, research output
presented in national/ international forum, attendance to research undertakings,
and to the chosen researcher of the year. There are two levels of awards that are
being given by the University, namely: the campus level and the university level.
There are criteria for the selection of researcher of the year and the awards are
given during the University Foundation Anniversary Celebration (University
Research manual, p.27-29, Criteria on p. 29-34).

         It is also an institutional policy to assign corresponding workload units for
the performance of the functions to ensure fairness and to set criteria for
additional incentives that are based on excess workload units (Research
Manual).

         Students’ efforts in research are also given recognition by conferring “Best
Thesis Award” to the student researchers whose research study has been
proven outstanding/ exemplary among other researches. This recognition is
given during their Commencement Exercises.

         The College researchers, both faculty and students, have been given
corresponding recognition for a research achievement as shown in the list below:

     Faculty Recipient      Title of Award/Recognition      Granting Agency  Inclusive Dates
Christianne Lynnette G.                                             Level
Cabanban                 Certificate of Recognition(Paper
Duran, Isidro L.         Presentation)                      DMMMSU-SLUC      January 2014
Munar, Emely A.
Marzan, Charlie S.       Certificate of Recognition (Paper  DMMMSU-SLUC      January 2014
Songcuan, Jerome P.      Presentation)
Dacanay, Enrico G.                                          DMMMSU-SLUC      January, 2013
Soria, Agnes B.          Certificate of Recognition
Tambot, Kathrina S.      (Research Publication)             DMMMSU-CCS       SY.2012-2013

                         Best Undergraduate Thesis          DMMMSU-CCS       SY 2009-2010 | SY
                         Adviser(College Level)             DMMMSU-CCS       2011-2012

                         Best Undergraduate Thesis                           SY.2008-2009
                         Adviser(College Level)
                                                            DMMMSU-CCS       SY.2008-2009 |
                         Best Undergraduate Thesis          DMMMSU-CCS       SY.2009-2010
                         Adviser(College Level)
                                                                             SY. 2010-2011
                         Best Undergraduate Thesis
                         Adviser(College Level)

                         Best Undergraduate Thesis
                         Adviser(College Level)

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 78]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

         In the year 2012-2013, there were faculty members who have received
appreciation from outside organizations:

  Name of              Title of Research                  Year                Conferring Body
Researcher               Output/Award                 Presented/
                                                       Received   International Association for
Isidro L. Duran        Relative Effectiveness of                  Multidisciplinary Research
                       Virtual Laboratory Strategies      2013
                       in Teaching Physics/

                       Best in Oral Presentation
                       Best in Powerpoint

                        Presentation(2nd place)

                       Meta-Analysis on the Role of   2013        La Consolacion College
                       Mathematics Background in      2013        (cooperating agencies: Intl Assn of
                       the Performance of BSCS                    Multidisciplinary Research
                       Freshmen in Computer                       (IAMURE), Phil. Assn of Institutions
                       Programming Subjects/                      for Research (PAIR), Commission
                                                                  on Higher Education (CHED), Nat’l
Agustin R. Veras, Jr.  Best Oral Presentation                     Organization of Science Teachers
                       (Platinum Award)                           and Educators (NOSTE)
                       Proposed Blended Learning
                       Program for                                International Association for
                       Don Mariano Marcos                         Multidisciplinary Research
                       Memorial State University
                       South La Union Campus
                       (DMMMSU-SLUC)/

Charlie S. Marzan      Best in Oral Presentation      2012        Philippine elearning Society in
                       Best in Powerpoint                         cooperation
                                                                  with Siliman University
                          Presentation

                       iLearn: A Courseware for
                       Professional Courses of the
                       College of Computer Science
                       DMMMSU-SLUC/

                       Best Paper

    Currently, the College plans to continue engaging in these activities and
improve its performance in research. It aims to continually involve its faculty,
students, and stakeholders in research both in its conduct, dissemination, and
implementation (please see Appendix R and S).

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 79]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Extent of compliance to the recommendations in Area V (Research) in the
    last survey visit.

Recommendations            Actions Taken                    Percentage of  Remarks
                                                          Accomplishment

1. The unit may            Presentation of the            100%             Continuous
consider inviting          research agenda for review                         activity
government agency          has been conducted by the
representatives, other     University which was
stakeholders and           participated by stakeholders
beneficiaries in crafting  and beneficiaries.
and planning the
research agenda of the     Research agenda has been
college.                   presented to students and
                           faculty. Students are also
                           invited in college meetings.

                           Stakeholders/ beneficiaries

                           have been invited during
                           students’ thesis defense

2. There is a need to      The faculty have been          65%              On-going
source out and/or          actively participating in
strengthen linkages        research conferences and
with national and          presentations nationally and
international funding      internationally, and have
agencies for research      been involving themselves
activities.                to memberships for future
                           research undertakings.

3. The administration      Memorandum of agreement        100%                                Done
may reconsider             is signed by the two parties   100%                                Done
allocating fair research   to establish affiliation-- in
budget by degree           the OJT of students, and
offering based on          project development
approved research          Recommendations have
proposal.                  been presented to the
                           administration to reconsider
4. If budget warrants,     allocating fair budget by
the administration may     degree offering based on
allocate fund for the      approved researches.
purchase of licensed       In-house reviews are also
statistical software to    being conducted where
                           researches and budget are
                           presented for approval and
                           funding.
                           Recommendation has been
                           presented to the
                           administration, SPSS
                           statistical software
                           purchased

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 80]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

  Recommendations          Actions Taken                   Percentage of  Remarks
                                                         Accomplishment
be used in research
activities.                Also, purchase of a licensed
                           statistical software for the
                           College is included in its
                           2015 procurement plan

5. The unit may            The College started           60%              On-going
consider establishing      developing a system where     100%               Done
record system of the       records, information, and
research outputs, the      other important documents
income derived, and its    may be stored and filed.
distribution.              There is an existing
                           procedure that reports/
6. The unit may            records research outputs,
reconsider revisiting the  and activities.
Faculty Development        The recommendation has
Program for verticalized   been presented to the
graduate degree            College administration to
program.                   revisit the Faculty
                           Development Program
                           (Faculty Development
                           Program revisited)

7. The unit is             Faculty members conduct       100%             Continuing
encouraged to have full    research                                         activity
participation in planning
and implementing           The College is represented
research activities in     in conferences, seminars,
collaborative and          and planning workshops
interdisciplinary manner   conducted by the University
                           and other organizations

                           The college is involved/
                           participated in
                           institutionalized researches
                           such as Graduate Tracer
                           study and Student Services
                           study.

8. While researches        There is ongoing              100%                                 Done
have been published in     collaboration with other
the University             units for the attainment of
Research and               the research thrusts which
Extension Journal and      are included in the
                           operational plan
                           There is a policy that the
                           University will shoulder
                           expenses for the publication
                           of research results in a
                           journal provided that the

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 81]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer Science We code to innovate…

Recommendations           Actions Taken                   Percentage of  Remarks
                                                        Accomplishment

other papers and          study has undergone the
presented in different    procedures required by the
fora, the administration  University and has met the
may shoulder the          requirements stated in the
expenses in the           policy
publication of research
results in refereed
journal.

9. The University may     Research abstracts have       80%              Continuing
consider the use of the   been uploaded in the                             activity
University website for a  College website
faster, easier and wider
publication and           Certificate of Acceptance is
dissemination of          secured from the student
research outputs.         developers to ensure that
                          the research output has
                          been presented and
                          accepted by their
                          beneficiary/ client.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science  Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit 82]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

                           FACULTY DEVELOPMENT

1. WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES

    a. University
           The Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University (DMMMSU)

    envisions to become a premier and globally competitive university by
    providing advanced instruction in the Arts, Agriculture, Forestry, Fisheries,
    Engineering and Natural Sciences as well as in the Technological and
    Professional fields, to promote research and engaged in extension works.
    DMMMSU leads in transforming human resources into productive self-reliant
    citizens and responsible leaders.

           The mandate of university education are carried out and realized through
    the faculty. Aligned with its vision-mission, the DMMMSU provides
    appropriate and relevant educational experiences to faculty members who are
    at the forefront of instruction, research, and community engagement in their
    specific disciplines. The faculty defines the image, formidability, and character
    of an institution that virtually asserts a strategic essence in building a nation
    with its sovereignty and development agenda. Equipped with competencies
    and commitment, the faculty members can steer a university to excellence.
    The College of Computer Science aims to upgrade its instruction, research,
    and extension services through a functional faculty development program to
    enable it to better respond to development needs of the region and the nation.

    b. College of Computer Science
         OBJECTIVES OF THE FACULTY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM

    1. To facilitate continuing professional development of at least 75% of the
         faculty members.

    2. To reinforce significant number of faculty members to conduct scholarly
         researches of international and national levels.

    3. To engage all faculty members in extension services
    4. To develop scientific and technical solutions to facilitate operations of the

         institution and other agencies.

2. ADEQUATE AND RELEVANT PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES TO ACHIEVE
OBJECTIVES

         To facilitate continuing professional development of at least 75%
of the faculty members.

         The College of Computer Science has a pool of eligible and highly
professional core faculty members who are competent in terms of academic
qualifications and professional expertise.

         Faculty development program of the college provides systematic and
attainable agenda in human resource development. These include completion of
post graduate studies vertically aligned to their baccalaureate degree; acquire
competencies and eligibilities, membership to recognized ICT organization and
participation to national and international seminars. The college maintains to
support the growth of faculty as it rationalizes and endorses faculty members to
university training/scholarship programs.

         The following shows the standings of the whole faculty as to professional
development:

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit83]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

A. Post Graduate Studies                                             DIT
                                                                     DIT w/units
                  Highest Degree Earned                              MIT/MIS/MCS/MA
                                                                     MIT/MCS -w/units
                                                        3%
                      19% 7%

                                                71%

                 Figure 13. Educational Attainment of Faculty members

         The figure shows the standing of the core faculty of the College of
Computer Science. From among the 32 faculty members, two (2) or 7% have
already finished Doctor in Information Technology (DIT) and one (1) faculty
member or 3% is about to finish his DIT. On the other hand, twenty three (23)
or 71% are holders of master’s degree. These include Masters in Information
Technology, Masters in Computer Science, Masters in Information System
and allied course, Masters in Education major in Math. Six (6) or 9% of the
faculty members are still pursuing their master’s degrees and are expected
to finish not later than 2016 (see Appendix T).

         As reflected in the College Development Program, faculty members
have already programmed activities pursuing MSCS and Ph. D in Computer
Science to attain vertical articulation (refer to Appendix Y).

B. Capability building/skills and competencies upgrading

                 Certificates and Eligibilities

                   100%            84%                               Opernsource Certification
                    80%                                              EDP/Licensed Professions
Number of Faculty                                                    CSC Eligibility
                   60% 40% 41%                                       AQ and TQ
                                                                     NC IV
                   40%                                               NC II

                   20%        13%       13%
                         6%

                   0%
                         Different Certifications and Eligibilities

                   Figure14. Certifications and eligibilities acquired by faculty
                                                  members

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit84]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

             Figure 14 depicts the certifications and eligibilities acquired by the
    core faculty members. Two (2) or 9% of them have gained open source
    certification particularly the Google App Certified Teacher and Ubuntu.
    Two (2) of the faculty members have passed the professional board exam
    awarded by PRC and another two (2) have obtained the Electronic Data
    Processing eligibility of the CSC which consist 13% of the faculty
    members. Furthermore, twenty seven (27) or 84% of the faculty are
    awarded professional eligibility by the Civil Service Commission. As for
    TESDA certifications, the standings of the faculty members are as follows:
    Thirteen (13) or 41% passed PC Hardware Servicing or National
    Certificate II, four (4) or 13% of the faculty members obtained the National
    Certificate in Structural and Object Oriented Programming or NC IV, and
    another twelve (12) or 40% are qualified assessor and trainer in NC II.

             Aside from the mentioned certifications and eligibilities, faculty
    members are also to pursue other international certifications like Google
    and CISCO. The college plans to increase the number of certified faculty
    members; thus, the administration have allotted are reasonable amount
    for this cause (please see Appendix Y).

C. Seminars/workshops/trainings relevant to the Program attended by
    the faculty members

                     Trainings and Seminars

28%     5% 18%                    International
   28%                       21%  National
                                  Regional
                                  Local
                                  Institutional

                     Figure 15. Trainings and Seminars of Faculty members

                  Figure 15 highlights the trainings, seminars, workshops, and
         conferences attended by the faculty members for the last three years. In a
         detailed view, sixteen (16) or 5% of faculty have attended international
         level, fifty six (56) or 18% in the national level, sixty seven(67) or 21% in
         the regional level, eighty nine (89) or 28% in the local level, and 88 or 28%
         in the institutional level (see Appendix X).

                  The college prioritizes on conferences which are appropriate and
         align to the field of specialization and relevant in updating of strategies
         and approaches in instruction. It has a systematic process in approving

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit85]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…
         funds for each of the conferences attended by the faculty members which
         is reflected in the College budget procurement plan.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit86]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

Faculty’s affiliation in professional/scientific organizations and honor
societies relevant to the Program.

                 Membership of Faculty Members to
                               Organizations

11% 17%  International
72%      National
         Local

               Figure16. Affiliation of faculty members to organizations

         Figure 16shows the percentage of the international, national and local
professional organizations and societies where core faculty members are
affiliated. Faculty members are associated to sixteen (16) national
organization or 72% of the total number. These include Philippine e-Learning
Society (PeLS), Philippine Society of Information Technology Educators,
Philippine National eLearning Association, among others. Moreover, six (6)
which composed 17% of the faculty are affiliated in international organizations
like British Computer Society-Chartered Institute for IT, Ubuntu Community,
Internet Society, and others while the remaining 11% belong to two (2) local
organization which is the Educators League of Agoo and DMMMSU Faculty
Association (please see Appendix U).

         The college plans to continue the good number of membership to
professional societies in the national level and increase its affiliation to the
international community (refer to Appendix Y).

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit87]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

D. Professional growth of the faculty members according to rank

     Academic Rank

     3%        3%      Assoc Prof 1
          10%      6%  Asst Prof IV

56%                                       Asst Prof II
               22%
                       Asst Prof I

                       Instructor 2

                       Instructor 1

                   Figure 17. Academic rank of faculty members

         Figure17 reflects the academic rank of core faculty members.
Twenty (20) of them or 61% are Instructor I; six (6) or 18% are Instructor
II; two (2) or 6% are Assistant Professor I; one (1) or 3% is Assistant
Professor II, three (3) or 9% is Assistant Professor IV and one (1) or 3% is
Associate Professor I (please see Appendix T).

         The University pursues and continually sustains equitable growth
and development of faculty and staff in recognition of fairness. It adheres
to the merit and fitness principle in the promotion and appointment of
faculty and staff.

         To reinforce significant number of faculty members to conduct
scholarly researches of international and national levels.

         The college aims to upgrade the involvement of faculty members in
the conduct of research. As spearheaded by University Research and
Extension Unit heads, in-house reviews of researches are conducted. Due
to active monitoring of the college research facilitators, the number of
faculty members engaging in research activity is evident.

         As for 2011 to present, 72% have published researches while 31%
of them have presented their study in international, national, and regional
for a (see Figure 11).

         Furthermore, the college engages other agencies to pool resources
on funded researches. It has built ties with agencies like the Government
of Malaysia, CHED, and Municipality of Agoo.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit88]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

       To engage all faculty members in extension services
                  The college is driven to provide its stakeholders in a given field of

         specialization. Every faculty member is oriented to adhere with the four-
         fold functions of the university which include the involvement of each
         faculty to extension programs. These activities provide annual training to
         elementary, secondary, tertiary public school teachers, and other
         professionals in La Union. These activities are Computer Literacy Training
         Program (CLTP), Advanced Computer Skills Development Training
         Program (ACSDTP),Computer Literacy Training Program for Educators in
         the 2nd District of La Union, Share-A-Ware Program for the Grade VI
         Pupils, Professor-in-the-Barangay, Literacy Training Program for the
         Barangay, and Consultancy Services.

                  Plans for extension programs of the college are discussed by
         Faculty members prior to the start of the school year and is monitored and
         evaluated by the Head of Extension.

                   Research of faculty members also focus on the improvement of
         services rendered to clienteles. Three (3) researches were conducted that
         served as benchmark of appropriate extension activities to be rendered by
         the college.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit89]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

Faculty members have presented research papers to national and international
conferences.

CCS faculty workforce as they receive the Pamadayaw ti Umili award given by the
Municipality of Agoo recognizing the successful implementation of the CLTP and
ACSDTP.
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit90]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

             To develop scientific and technological solutions to facilitate
    operations of the institution and other agencies.

             Inasmuch as the college engages its faculty members to
    instruction, research, extension, they are also tapped in producing
    technological and scientific products. Some of these activities include
    research based instructional materials, research based systems and
    system development program.

A. Faculty members produce research based modules
             To further deliver an effective and appropriate education to

    students, and on computer literacy program, instructional materials were
    produced. There are researches that were conducted which contributed to
    the improvement of instructional processes.

                      Instructional Materials

32%                               Developed
      21%  47%

                                  On Going

                                  Proposed

                    Figure 18. Percentage of Instructional materials of faculty
                                                  members

                  Figure 18 identifies the percentage on the development of
         instructional modules of faculty members in the college. Nine (9) or 47%
         were developed which are used in the courses offered in the college while
         others are utilized in computer literacy extension programs. Four (4) or
         21% are in the process of development while six (6) or 32% are still in the
         proposal stage.

    B. Faculty members produce research based systems.
                  The different systems developed by faculty members are verified,

         validated, and tested prior to implementation. This is through the conduct
         of usability researches which evaluates the functional operations in
         accordance to the specifications of the end users.

                   These researches have provided six (6) computerized systems to
         organizations which include: Agoo Unified ID System, Ordinance and
         Resolution Digital Archiving System, Management Information System for
         Children (MISC) of the Municipality of Agoo, Management Information

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit91]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

         System for Employees (MISE) of the Municipality of Agoo, Municipal
         Ordinance Historical Tracking System and DMMMSU-SLUC Automated
         Enrolment System.

                  The university recognizes the faculty members for developing
         numerous systems for the Municipality of Agoo.

    C. Engagement of faculty members to system development program
                  Faculty members are tapped by the institution and other agencies

         to develop systems and websites. The team headed by Jerome P.
         Songcuan, the MIS Head of the campus and a faculty of the college, was
         also able to provide and continuously maintain systems.

                  They have served the campus in producing systems like the Online
         Human Resource Information System, Computerized Trip Ticket of SLUC,
         and Record Management Archiving of SLUC. They also sustain the
         DMMMSU-SLUC website, CGS Website and the OPAC, a system used by
         the library.

                  The faculty members also advocate paperless office as it follows
         measures that maximizes the use of technology other than the traditional
         paper system. Administrators issue e-memorandum and posts
         announcements through online groups and social media. CCS Online
         Accomplishment Report is also uploaded where they can input their
         accomplishment every month. It is also a tool in assessing the submission
         of faculty members. As far as research is concerned, a CCS Research
         Compendium is also available that serves as a storage of researches of
         both faculty and students. A good archiving mechanism is also followed in
         the college. Reports like the syllabi operational and development plans,
         certificates of faculty and other pertinent documents are accumulated and
         digitally stored.

                  The college MIS facilitator introduced the use of Google Apps for
         education. It provides 30G capacity in the Google drive were faculty
         members could store up projects of students submitted online. It also
         offers applications in Google App, provide virtual classrooms, and platform
         for creating documents. Some faculty members, on the other hand,
         require students to pass activities online and perform LAN-based quizzes.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit92]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

    2. SYSTEMATIC AND EFFECTIVE PROCEDURES
                  The College of Computer Science faculty members always adhere

         to the University Faculty Manual, University Administrative Manual, and
         Student Handbook that guide in the management of human resource,
         administration, and student conduct, respectively. These manuals help in
         strengthening the vision of the university in providing quality service to its
         stakeholders by focusing on the policies and guidelines on faculty
         conduct, in relation to its objectives. As measures, development and
         operational plans as well as monitoring and evaluative measures are
         undertaken.

     Operational Plan
             o Each faculty member prepares an operational plan that includes the
                  quadric-fold functions of instruction, research, extension, and
                  production. This is prepared and submitted before the start of every
                  term. For effective and efficient implementation and monitoring of
                  the operational plan, accomplishment reports are submitted by the
                  faculty member.

     Faculty Workload
             o In order for faculty to develop an understanding of their roles, it is
                  an institutional policy to assign corresponding workload units in the
                  performance of the four-fold function as mandated by Higher
                  Educational Institutions. Workload includes activities in Instruction,
                  Research, Extension, and Production.

                o

     Faculty Performance Evaluation
             o The Faculty Performance Evaluation System (FPES) in DMMMSU
                  is an approach to evaluate faculty performance in their various
                  functions. It is administered in such manner as to continually foster
                  the improvement of individual employee efficiency and
                  organizational effectiveness. It is a tool to keep track of the
                  teacher’s progress and development and in designing ways and
                  means to improve teaching competencies. Form 1 or the evaluation
                  instrument for instruction (Teaching Effectiveness) is used in the
                  evaluation. This is executed by their immediate supervisor, peers
                  and students. Faculty members are evaluated every term to
                  measure their teaching effectiveness.

     Faculty Development Plan
             o Each faculty prepares both long-term and short-term development
                  plans. This helps enhance the overall performance and reputation
                  of a faculty. It also provides general guidelines to assist the faculty
                  member achieve its objective to help make tangible and significant
                  contributions to their discipline. Also, the faculty as a whole drafts
                  its long term faculty development plan as basis of budget allocation
                  on faculty development (see Appendix Y).

    3. REASONABLE BUDGET
             o Budget Allocation. The college dean submits internal operating
                  budget every six month of the year to be reviewed, evaluated, and
                  consolidated by the budget committee of the university. As reflected
                  in the faculty operational plan, the administration has allocated

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit93]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

                  budget intended for trainings, seminars, and membership to various
                  IT organizations.
             o Budget Programming. All faculty members participate in the
                  budget programming and reprogramming of the college. The dean
                  presents the initial budget plan to be reviewed and discussed by
                  the body. Areas that need more allocation are identified and
                  reconsidered.
             o Income Generating Projects. The college procures additional
                  funds for its operation from various projects. The college caters a
                  computer rental shop, software development project initiated by
                  faculty, rental of buildings and IT facilities, and the one-stop shop
                  for CCS merchandises.

             o University Compensation
                           Faculty members in the university have an advantage

                  among others as far as compensations are concerned.
                      Basic Incentives
                           a. Personal Emergency Relief Allowance (PERA) and
                               Additional Compensation (ADCOM)
                               All faculty members, whether permanent or temporary,
                               are entitled to a monthly PERA and ADCOM.
                           b. Year-end Bonus and Cash Gift
                               RA No. 6686, as implemented by the National
                               Compensation Circular No. 54, both dated December 4,
                               1988, provides for an annual year-end bonus equivalent
                               to one-month salary known as 13th Month Bonus and a
                               cash gift of Php 5,000.00 to all government officials and
                               employees who have rendered at least four (4) months of
                               service with pay from January 1 to October 31.
                           c. Clothing Allowance
                               A faculty, regardless of status, provided he/she has
                               rendered six (6) months of service at the time of payment
                               and should stay for another six (6) months after payment,
                               is entitled of clothing allowance.
                           d. Productivity Incentive Bonus (PIB)
                               A faculty member with permanent, full-time, or temporary
                               appointment who has rendered at least one year service
                               in the government with a performance rating of at least
                               satisfactory is entitled to a productivity incentive bonus.
                           e. Step Increment Based on Length of Service
                               This is given to a regular faculty member who has
                               rendered at least three (3) years of continuous service in
                               a particular position. This incentive shall consist of salary
                               step increments in accordance with the provisions of
                               Joint CSC-DBM Circular No. 1, series of 1990.
                           f. FAD CNA Incentive
                               A member of the Faculty Association of DMMMSU is
                               entitled to CNA incentive, the amount of which depends
                               on the savings of the agency, and is given at the end of
                               the year.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit94]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

                           g. Anniversary Bonus
                               At the anniversary of the university, an anniversary bonus
                               may be granted to each faculty.

                           h. Non-monetary Incentive
                               a) Service Credits
                                        A faculty earns service credit/s for overload and/or
                               rendering service during off-periods with prior approval
                               from the university President subject to existing rules and
                               regulations.
                               b) Compensatory Overtime Credit (COC)
                                        A faculty may work overtime and be remunerated
                               by earning compensatory overtime credit which may be
                               used at a later time. However, Compensatory Overtime
                               Credit earned is non-commutable and non-cumulative.
                               Such leave credits earned must be used only within the
                               year these were earned.

             *Source: DMMMSU Faculty Manual, Revised 2011

    4. PROVISION OF MATERIALS AND OTHER RESOURCES

                           Pursuant of the CSC rules on personal management for
                  career and personnel development, which includes performance
                  appraisal, promotion, training and scholarship programs; the
                  university has developed the Revised Merit System and Promotion
                  plan, Faculty Performance System as basic guideline for career
                  development.

                  Faculty Development Program
                       To maximize the educational benefits and privileges of the
                           faculty for degrees vertically aligned to their specialization,
                           scholarships are granted. Scholars are entitled to salaries
                           and benefits, tuition and other school fees, monthly stipend,
                           book allowance, and thesis/dissertation aid.

                  Scholarship for Dependents
                           Children of faculty members may enjoy free tuition fee during
                           the entire duration of their study at DMMMSU subject to
                           approved policies on scholarships.

                  Scholarship of the Faculty to Undergraduate Courses in the
                           University
                            A faculty who enrolls in the undergraduate program related
                           to his/her assignment is entitled to free tuition fee subject to
                           approved policies on scholarships except in the College of
                           Law.

                  Provision of IT Equipment and Office Supplies
                           Along with the sufficient number of computers in laboratory
                           rooms, laptops, LCD multimedia projectors and office
                           supplies are provided to faculty members to deliver quality
                           instruction as well as in the discharge of other functions in
                           research, extension and production. As of record, there are
                           thirty two (32) laptops and twenty-six (26) multimedia LCD
                           projectors which are available for the faculty to use. Sound

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit95]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

                           systems and LCD platforms are also available in each of the
                           laboratory which faculty can utilize.
         Suggestion and Incentive Award System
                           The university acknowledges inventions, superior
                           accomplishments of faculty and efforts through appropriate
                           recognition. The Suggestion ad Incentive Award Committee
                           (SIAC) identifies these faculty members who are given
                           preferences in promotion and training grants/ scholarship.

PARTICIPATION OF SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF
FACULTY/STAFF/STUDENTS/ COMMUNITY IN MAJOR
PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES

                      The university ensures that faculty members pursue holistic
             development not only focusing on scholarly works but in developing
             their physical and socio-cultural aspects as well. The institution
             organizes activities that enable faculty members to strengthen
             camaraderie among them. These activities are spearheaded by the
             Faculty Association of DMMMSU together with the Campus and
             University administrations. Faculty get to join sporting events and Laro
             ng Lahi type of games as well as cultural events like singing
             competitions, writing, dance competitions, and even pageants. Faculty
             Day is celebrated in the university where they get together and take
             pleasure in the different team building activities while faculty fora are
             also observed to address issues that concern them. Furthermore, the
             university identifies exemplary faculty members who are given
             distinction during University Foundation Day.

                      The college also manages to continue activities intended for
             faculty members. In- service trainings are organized every month and
             team building is observed each year.

                      As to extension activities, faculty members serve as resource
             speakers as well as facilitators. Over the years, faculty members have
             participated in educating teachers and other professionals in Agoo.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit96]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

         The University adheres to the total development of its faculty members
such as organizing Faculty Olympics and other activities for each school year.

  Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit97]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

         The college conducts in-house trainings each month and team building
activities each school year.
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit98]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

5. AWARDS OF DISTINCTION AND ACHIEVEMENT AND GRANTS OF
    THE PROGRAM

Awards

                            Awards

                                           15% 8%
                                                                            International
                                                                            National

                     77% Institutional

               Figure 19. Awards received by the faculty members

         Faculty members of the College of Computer Science are also
recognized by local, national, and international award giving bodies. It can
also be noted that they are awarded which are very relevant to their
respective disciplines. Two (2) or 15% of the faculty members have
received awards internationally; one (1) or 8 % accepted awards
nationally, and 10 or 77% obtained institutional awards (see Appendix V)

Scholarship Grants                                          International Scholar
                                                            National Scholar
                                Grants                      University Scholars
                                                            Theis Aid Grantee
                                                       25%

          25%

          20%

         15% 13%
                                               9%

          10%

                            3%

            5%

            0%

               Figure 20. Scholarships and grants awarded to faculty members

         Figure 20exhibits the provisions to faculty members in terms of grants and
aids. As for the record, one (1) or 3% of the faculty members have acquired a

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit99]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[DMMMSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…
competitive type of scholarship in Thailand. Four (4) or 13% have received a
national scholarship which was awarded by the Commission on Higher Education
and this was used in pursuing a Master’s in Information Technology degree.
Furthermore, three (3) of the faculty members or 9% have pursued their Doctor in
Information Technology while eight (8) or 25% have received their thesis aid
which were all supported by the university (see also Appendix W).

         The scholarship funds from CHED and the university made it possible for
these faculty members to pursue and finish their doctorate and master’s degree.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit100]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

Extent of compliance to the recommendations in Area II (Faculty) in the last
survey visit.

Recommendations        Action taken                    Percentage Remarks
                                                             of

                                                       compliance

1. The college may     Faculty members have            90%   Continuing
consider updating      participated in-house review            activity
lecture notes through  where they have presented
an interface of        researches with worktexts
relevant research      and modules to be
findings and new       developed as outputs. There
knowledge.             were also researches
                       presented on the evaluation
                       of student performance in
                       programming subjects where
                       different factors were
                       identified and addressed.

2. Measures to avoid   Two (2) faculty members         80%   Continuing
professional-          have finished Doctorate                 activity
inbreeding may be      degree in Information
considered to help in  Technology (DIT) at St. Paul
the attainment of a    University and AMA
world class            University, respectively.
university.            Also, one (1) faculty finished
                       Master in Computer Science
                       (MCS) Degree at University
                       of Cordilleras and another
                       one (1) faculty member is
                       pursuing the same program,
                       DIT at the University of the
                       Cordilleras.

                       Faculty members are
                       required to pursue graduate
                       and post-graduate degrees
                       format least Level II
                       accredited colleges and
                       universities.

3. The college may     Faculty members were sent       100%  Done
revisit the faculty    to national and international
development plan       trainings and seminars.
and encourage
faculty to             The college has crafted a
continuously pursue    faculty development plan
advance education,     pursuant to an advanced
preferably Ph. D. in   education program of faculty
                       members which is related to
                       its program offering.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit101]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[MSU-SLUC- College of Computer ScienceWe code to innovate…

Recommendations          Action taken               Percentage Remarks
                                                          of

                                                    compliance

Computer Science
where possible and
available to make it
more fitting to the
program being
offered.

4. The allocated         Portion of the budget was  100%  Done
budget for faculty       programmed for faculty
development may be       developments reflected in
increased to further     the CCS operational plan.
strengthen the faculty
in the college.

5. The documents to      Relevant documents are     100%  Done
be presented should      signed by the concerned
be signed by             authorities.
concerned authority
to make it official and
legal.

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Level III – Phase 2 Accreditation Survey Visit102]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>